<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Succinct description of France wherein is a character of the people, customs, &amp;c. of that kingdom : sent by a gentleman now travelling there, to his friend in England : dedicated to that eminent and learned physician, Dr. Martin Lister, and may serve as a supplement to his Journey to Paris.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6114A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12165934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12165934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 116:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Succinct description of France wherein is a character of the people, customs, &amp;c. of that kingdom : sent by a gentleman now travelling there, to his friend in England : dedicated to that eminent and learned physician, Dr. Martin Lister, and may serve as a supplement to his Journey to Paris.</title>
                  <author>Philo-Patriae, Eugenius.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Pseudo-patriae [pseud.].</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Eugenius Philo-Patriae [pseud.].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Succinct DESCRIPTION OF FRANCE, Wherein is a CHARACTER OF THE <hi>People, Cuſtoms,</hi> &amp;c. OF THAT KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>Sent by a Gentleman now Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling there, to his Friend in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated to that Eminent and Learned Phyſician, Dr. <hi>MARTIN LISTER;</hi> and may ſerve as a Supplement to his Journey to
<hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED Dr. <hi>Martin Liſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SOme ill natured and unthinking Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals having imbib'd an Opinion that your only Deſign in publiſhing your Journey to <hi>Paris,</hi> was to flatter the <hi>French</hi> and diſparage the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they made, you know, very undecent Reflections upon that Treatiſe, repreſented your Worſhip as a ſhort ſighted, prejudiced Obſerver, and one that had a greater Eſteem and Veneration for <hi>Paris</hi> than the famous City of <hi>London:</hi> Which in reſpect of its healthful and pleaſant Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſplendid and uniform Buildings, Houſes and Shops richly Furniſhed, wealthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Tradeſmen, and excellency of its
<pb facs="tcp:55316:3"/>Government, is Celebrated as a <hi>Non-Pareil</hi> through the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, as Ignorance is the Parent of Miſunderſtanding, ſo they were unhappily led into this Miſtake for want of Brains to comprehend your Method in commending and diſpraiſing. For your Abilities in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, like the other parts of your great Learning, lying very deep, and out of the Vulgar Track, it is not diſcernible to every Pur-blind Eye: Whereas better illuminated Apprehenſions eaſily perceiv'd your Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to give the Preference for <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Engliſh-men;</hi> for when you ſpake of the <hi>French</hi> City and People, your Elogies were Satyrs, your Panegyricks Lampoons, and you always unluckily brought in ſomething that diſparag'd what you ſeem'd to advance, and clouded all the Glory that was thought you intended them in the publication of your Journey.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, you ſay the <hi>French</hi> Gentry <hi>are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Civil and Obliging,</hi> and I believe no leſs, though you are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>They value themſelves upon their Courtſhip, and in making a Leg and Bow better than the reſt of Mankind: Building and Dreſſing moſtly for Figure, and that their principal Diverſions are only to ſee and be ſeen;</hi> and this I think, Sir, your Enemies will allow to be no extraordinary Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:3"/>
            <p>You acquaint us, Sir, <hi>That their Houſes are richly furniſhed; for they have generally from five to ten diſtinct Families under every Roof, that the Inhabitants are wealthy in Pictures,</hi> and have the Curioſity and Ingenuity <hi>to Ruin themſelves in that kind of expenſive Furniture:</hi> Which would be thought a vanity in others; but this, Doctor, is your peculiar knack in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending their Oeconomy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Buildings in</hi> Paris, you ſay, <hi>are very fine, built with rough Stone, Plaiſter'd over, and Colour'd to make them look like Brick; but at longeſt, will not ſtand above five and twenty Years,</hi> and then they have the pleaſure of building new ones, which muſt needs be a great ſatisfaction to the Proprietors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paris</hi> in your Opinion, Sir, <hi>is more Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous than</hi> London, <hi>but it ſeems 'tis only in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, becauſe the Palaces and Convents have eat up the Peoples Dwellings, and crowded them ſo exceſſively together in the Trading parts of the Town, that they ſeem more numerous than they are; whereas the Artiſts and Tradeſmen in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>have purchaſed the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemens Palaces, and converted them into Shops and private Dwellings. The lower Windows in</hi> Paris <hi>are grated with ſtrong Iron Bars before 'em.</hi> But are excelled in that particular alſo, if you had thought upon't by the two ſtately Houſes over the two <hi>Weſt</hi> Gates of <hi>London.</hi> You ſay alſo <hi>That</hi> Paris <hi>is a beautiful and convenient
<pb facs="tcp:55316:4"/>City but the Streets are very narrow, extreamly dirty, and the Paſſengers on foot no way ſecured from the hurry and danger of Coaches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Above all, <hi>You ſay their Gardens are very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things,</hi> and well they may be ſo, for you are pleaſed to add as a Character of their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, <hi>That as ſoon as a</hi> Frenchman <hi>gets any thing by Fortune or Inheritance, he will lay it out upon a Picture, or an Ornament for his Garden: Though many Utenſils and Conveniencies of Life are wanting to him which are common in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their Food in general,</hi> you ſay, <hi>Is courſe Bread and Lettice, but that indifferent Aliment is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd with plenty of Sauce, for you tell us they have abundance of Onions, Leeks, Garlick, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, Shallot, Rocombo's and Muſhrooms. Their Hackney-Coaches and Chairs are the moſt naſty and miſerable Voiture [Carriage] that can be, and yet are as dear again as in</hi> London; but that misfortune you ſay, <hi>is ſupply'd by a worſe,</hi> viz. <hi>The</hi> Vingrette, <hi>which is a Coach with two Wheels, dragg'd by a Man, and puſh'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind by a Woman or a Boy, and ſometimes by both,</hi> which you truly ſay <hi>is a wretched buſineſs in ſo magnificent a City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their Biſhops,</hi> ſay you, <hi>make the beſt Figure in the Town in their Equipages and Liveries, but not in reſpect of their Learning;</hi> for you are pleaſed to add, <hi>That Learning is not ſo neceſſary a Qualification there, as with us in</hi> England.
<pb facs="tcp:55316:4"/>
               <hi>Their Churches are numerous, but not big, and very few of them have either Towers or Steeples, though they are the Glory of a Proſpect;</hi> but at length, Sir, you are pleaſed to credit the <hi>French,</hi> and gratifie your Enemies, in ſaying, <hi>They have more manners and Religion than the</hi> Engliſh; for which, ſome of your Country-men are reſolv'd never to forgive you, though I think they juſtly ought, for the Characters you beſtow on their Monks. <hi>Who wear,</hi> ſay you, <hi>the Ruſtick Habits of old Times, without Shirts, or other Linnen Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the preſent Age. That wantonly Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute themſelves to do violence to Chriſtianity. That feed upon ſowre Herbs, Fiſh, and ſuch kind of Traſh, and lie worſe, always rough and upon Boards; go bare foot in a cold Country; deny themſelves the Comforts of this Life, and wear out their days in a ſlaviſh and fruitleſs Devotion.</hi> And this I think may at one for what your Back Friends call an odious Compariſon.</p>
            <p>Thus far, dear Doctor, I have been your Compurgator, and clear'd you from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion of being more a <hi>French-man</hi> than an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> which might have been prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to your Practice: And now am become an humble Suitor to you, that ſince a Friend that is gone a long Journey has oblig'd me with a Succinct and Pleaſant View of ſome parts of <hi>France;</hi> and largely Supplies in Words at length, where you mince the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that you would pleaſe to take it into
<pb facs="tcp:55316:5"/>your Protection, and give it the Honour of being Bound up as a Supplement with your <hi>Journey to Paris,</hi> and you will much oblige,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Humble Servant,</hi>
Philo-Patriae.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text_of_description">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55316:5"/>
            <head>A <hi>Succinct Deſcription</hi> OF FRANCE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Dear</hi> SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE notice of a happy Peace after ſo tedious a War, tempting our Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity to take a view of <hi>France,</hi> of which we have had ſuch different Relations; my ſelf, with ſeveral other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, embark'd at <hi>Dover</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> the pleaſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Month of the Year, with a fair South Weſt Wind, which had it continued in that Point, would ſoon have wafted us to the <hi>Galick</hi> Shoar; but a little toward Night it veering more about to the Weſt, and the Tide not befriending us, our Paſſage became tedious and troubleſom to ſuch Freſh-water Sailers, and we had leiſure to ſee the ſwelling Waves, by an inbred Ambition, ſtrive which ſhould be the higheſt; while our Veſſel by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55316:6"/>a violent agitation of the Wind danc'd a nimble <hi>Galiard</hi> on the Billows; but that which made the generality of the Paſſengers in a very uneaſy condition, and the Deck and Cabins look like ſo many <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> fill'd with diſeaſed Perſons; made the <hi>Scaly</hi> Inhabitants of that <hi>Watry Kingdom</hi> ſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on the ſurface of the Waves, and dance about our Ketch as if ſhe had been a mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>May-Pole,</hi> and acted their Meaſures with ſuch a delightful <hi>Decorum,</hi> as if they had been taught to <hi>Caper</hi> by the beſt of <hi>French</hi> Dancing Maſters. The next <hi>Ebb</hi> brought us within ſight of the Sea Coaſt of <hi>Normandy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> a Shoar ſo evenly compoſed and levelled, that it looks like the work of <hi>Art,</hi> and not of <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Inhabitants of this Country came
<note n="*" place="margin">Anno 800.</note> Originally from <hi>Norway,</hi> Soldiers of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and ſo terribly ſpoil'd the Maritine Coaſts of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> that, <hi>A furore Normannorum</hi> was inſerted into the <hi>Letany;</hi> but now being Conquer'd by the <hi>French,</hi> and enſlaved under that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, they are utterly creſt fallen, have loſt both their <hi>Courage</hi> and their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and nothing remains among them now of their Progenitors, but a penurious <hi>Pride,</hi> and an ungovernable <hi>Surlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Tide landed us at <hi>Deipe</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Town of</hi> Diepe.</note> A Town ſeated on an Arm of the Sea, between two Hills, which are a Security to the <hi>Harbour,</hi> and a Strength to the <hi>Town;</hi> but avail'd them little againſt the <hi>Courage</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the Force of their <hi>Bombs,</hi> whoſe Injuries they were now Repairing. The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55316:6"/>number of the Inhabitants were formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted about 30000, whereof 9000 of them were of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and the Church of <hi>Argues,</hi> a Village about two Miles from <hi>Deipe</hi> was allowed them for the Exerciſe of their Religion; but ſince the <hi>Perſecution</hi> they are all diſperſed, and the want of them greatly Lamented.</p>
            <p>Here we were Eye Witneſſes of the <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Popiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</note> in paying <hi>divine Honour</hi> to things <hi>Inanimate:</hi> We ſaw the <hi>Hoaſt</hi> or <hi>Sacrament</hi> carried through the Streets, by a couple of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> under a <hi>Canopy,</hi> uſher'd by two or three <hi>Torches,</hi> and followed by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Idle</hi> Boys and old People: Before it, was carried a <hi>Bell</hi> continually <hi>Tinkling,</hi> to warn the People that their <hi>God</hi> was carrying by, and expected their <hi>Reverence,</hi> which was paid by all that met it, by falling on their <hi>Knees,</hi> Raiſing their <hi>Heads,</hi> and giving it <hi>Honour:</hi> Tho' methinks not with ſo much Devotion, as I ſhould have done, if I had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved it, as they do, to be the <hi>Body</hi> of my <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I find its the Common practice of this Country,
<note place="margin">Their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling Chariots and Horſes.</note> for the <hi>Laity</hi> as well as the <hi>Clergy</hi> to impoſe upon Mens <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Underſtandings;</hi> for we deſigning to Travel towards <hi>Rouen,</hi> and Horſes being not to be had for Money, and the <hi>War</hi> between the two Nations, and the Ruins of <hi>Deipe,</hi> were ſo freſh in their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories we could not expect them for <hi>Love,</hi> we were forc'd to make uſe of the common Conveyance, and that was in a <hi>Cart;</hi> but for fear of Offending, forſooth, in ſpite of our Teeths, tho' we ſaw it was a <hi>Cart,</hi> we muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55316:7"/>call it <hi>Une Chariot,</hi> and to pleaſe them ſo we did, tho' we thought it fit for no <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph,</hi> but that of a <hi>French-man.</hi> To this <hi>Cart</hi> (Chariot I mean) were faſtened three things, that had been <hi>Horſes</hi> in their time, but were now skelitoniz'd into Carcaſes, or Images of Horſes, without life or motion. When we were mounted they began to Crawl, for go they could not, however it convinc'd me they had life, tho' I thought it would hold out no longer, than to carry them to the next Pack of Hounds. Thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated <hi>A la mode de France,</hi> we took our leaves of <hi>Deipe,</hi> and wagg'd ſo ſlowly towards <hi>Roven,</hi> that we thought our Journey was a perfect Emblem of the motion of the <hi>Ninth Sphere,</hi> which was Forty Nine Thouſand Years in finiſhing; but this was not all our Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the <hi>Rain</hi> fell on us through our <hi>Tilt,</hi> which for the many Holes in it, might more truly have been call'd a <hi>Net.</hi> The <hi>Dirt</hi> broke plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon us, through the <hi>Rails</hi> of our <hi>Chariot,</hi> and the unproportionable pace of it, ſtarted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every <hi>Bone</hi> of our Bodies. I wonder how a <hi>French-man,</hi> that commonly carries the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> of his Country about him, durſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture his craſy Carcaſs in it. Thus we endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all the infelicities of a Journey, and eſcaped three ſeveral <hi>Deaths,</hi> Drowning, Choaking with Mire, and Breaking of the Wheel; beſides the fear of being <hi>Famiſh'd</hi> before we came to our <hi>Inn,</hi> which was ſix <hi>French</hi> Miles from us.</p>
            <p>Not to mention the <hi>Beggarly</hi> Villages we dragled through,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Town and the Inn at</hi> Toſtes.</note> we came at laſt to <hi>Toſtes,</hi> the place deſtin'd for our Lodging; a Town like the <hi>Worſer</hi> ſort of our Market Towns in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55316:7"/>
               <hi>England.</hi> There our <hi>Chariotier</hi> brought us to the <hi>Ruins</hi> of a Houſe, an <hi>Alehouſe</hi> I would ſcarce have thought it, but in complement to the Nation, it muſt be cald an <hi>Inn;</hi> yes, and an Honourable one too, as <hi>Don Quixots</hi> Hoſt told him. Deſpair of finding in this <hi>Naſty hole,</hi> either Bedding or Victuals, I was in the Mans mind that choſe <hi>Hanging,</hi> rather than Marry a foul Queen that Beg'd him; and was often ready to ſay, <hi>Drive on Carman.</hi> The truth on't is, I fell out of the Frying-Pan into the Fire.</p>
            <p>A Courſe Fac'd <hi>Tatterdemalion</hi> belonging to the Houſe,
<note place="margin">The Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> brought us into a Room as <hi>Dark</hi> and as <hi>Damp</hi> as a <hi>Charnel-Houſe;</hi> only toward the <hi>Orchard</hi> there was a Melancholy kind of a <hi>Hole,</hi> which in Days of <hi>Yore,</hi> had been a <hi>Window,</hi> but now both Frame and Glaſs were vaniſh'd: However by the <hi>Light</hi> that came in, I could eaſily perceive I was not in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Chamber were three Beds,
<note place="margin">The Bedds and Sheets.</note> if it be Lawful to call them ſo, that were bottom'd with <hi>Straw,</hi> ſo cloſely ſqueez'd together, that the <hi>Wool-Packs,</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> in reſpect of theſe were <hi>Swans-Down.</hi> On this Straw <hi>Huddle</hi> lay a Medly of <hi>Flocks</hi> and <hi>Feathers,</hi> ſewed up in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> caſt <hi>Hop-Sack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo ill ordered, that they ſtuck up like the <hi>Knobbs</hi> of a Crab-Tree <hi>Cudgel,</hi> and we were obliged to our <hi>Fleſh,</hi> that one Nights Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing did not wear our <hi>Bones</hi> out. The <hi>Sheets</hi> they brought us, were ſo <hi>Courſe,</hi> that in my Conſcience, a Sailer would have refuſed them for a <hi>Hammock,</hi> and I heartily wiſh'd I could have exchang'd them for an <hi>Engliſh Horſe-Cloath;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55316:8"/>the <hi>Coverlid</hi> ſo courſe and Bare, that if a Man would have undertaken to have counted the <hi>Threds,</hi> he need not have miſs'd <hi>One</hi> of the Number.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Table Linnen</hi> was of the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
<note place="margin">The Table Linnen.</note> ſo <hi>Foul</hi> and <hi>Dirty,</hi> that I could not think it had been waſh'd above once, ſince it grew in the Hemp ground, and yet the poor things had as brisk a <hi>French</hi> Air, as if they had been promiſed for the next whole Year, to eſcape a <hi>Scouring.</hi> By this Deſcription of an <hi>Inn,</hi> you may gueſs Sir, at all the reſt in <hi>France.</hi> Some are not altogether ſo wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet the alteration is almoſt inſenſible.</p>
            <p>Let us now walk into the <hi>Kitchin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Proviſion for Supper.</note> and ſee what's for <hi>Supper,</hi> and here, Sir, we found a moſt terrible <hi>Execution,</hi> committed upon the body of a Pullet. Our <hi>Hoſteſs,</hi> cruel Woman as ſhe was, had cut the Throat of it, and without plucking off the <hi>Feathers,</hi> tore it into pieces, and then took off the <hi>Skin</hi> and <hi>Feathers</hi> together, as we ſtrip <hi>Rabbets</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> clapt it into a <hi>Pan,</hi> and <hi>Fricaſized</hi> it into a <hi>Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which Repaſt we had a Sight of our <hi>Hoſteſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our Hoſtes and her Daughter.</note> and her <hi>Daughter,</hi> at which we bleſt our Souls, and march off, leſt the fulſom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview ſhould have brought up what we had eaten; for ſuch a couple of <hi>dirty Queans</hi> was never ſeen in <hi>England,</hi> unleſs in a <hi>Duſt Cart,</hi> or among the Gold Finders at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. <hi>Horace</hi>'s Salutation, <hi>O mater pulchra filia pulchrior,</hi> was never ſo ſeaſonable as here. Not to honour them with a fairer Character let this ſuffice, that their <hi>Perſons</hi> kept ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a Decorum with the <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Furniture,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55316:8"/>that 'tis pitty they ſhould be parted. But this is not the luck of the Women of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> only, for through all <hi>France</hi> their <hi>Faces</hi> and their <hi>Linnen</hi> are the beſt Guards of their <hi>Chaſtity:</hi> They are all forc'd to be contented with a very little <hi>Beauty,</hi> and ſhe which with us would be ſlighted as an <hi>Antidote,</hi> or a meer dirty <hi>Doudy,</hi> would paſs with them for a <hi>Beautiful Princeſs;</hi> but more of the Women when we come to <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In their Habits the <hi>Normand</hi> Women dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the reſt of <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Womens Habits in</hi> Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> The Attire of their Heads, hangs down their Backs like a Vail, and looks like a Superannuated <hi>Diſh-Clout,</hi> turn'd out of Service, or the corner of a <hi>Table Cloath,</hi> that never had been waſh'd. Being ready to leave our Quarters in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we found our ſelves in a throng of <hi>Ill Faces,</hi> all Whining out <hi>Pour les Servantes,</hi> and our bounty was like giving a <hi>Dole,</hi> at a Rich Mans Funeral, you could not ſay when you had done giving, there were ſo many of them; and herein only was our Advantage, that their Ambition reaches no higher than a <hi>Sou a penny,</hi> and he that gives more over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids their <hi>Expectation,</hi> and ſhall be counted a <hi>Prodigal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of all the <hi>Gallantries of France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Men Servants.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to the <hi>Men-Servants</hi> in their <hi>Inns,</hi> the Raggedſt regiment that ever Eyes beheld, their cloths full of Patches, or open to their Skins, and by the habits of the <hi>Attendants,</hi> a man would be tempted to think he had been lodg'd in a <hi>Goal.</hi> Bid one of them give you a <hi>Cloth</hi> to wipe your hands, and he will reach you the <hi>Curtain</hi> of the <hi>Bed:</hi> Bid him wipe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55316:9"/>the <hi>Table,</hi> or your <hi>Bootes,</hi> he has ſtill recourſe to the <hi>Curtains,</hi> and they perform all their Offices, with their <hi>Hats</hi> on their <hi>Heads</hi> to which <hi>French Cuſtom</hi> I profeſs my ſelf an open <hi>Enemy;</hi> for tho' <hi>Jack</hi> ſpeaks French, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not allow <hi>Jack</hi> to be a <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we ſet out for <hi>Rouen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rouen <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</hi>
               </note> The whole journey was <hi>ſix</hi> French Miles, and our <hi>Cart</hi> was Ten hours in dragging us thither: Excellent ſpeed; and would have wore out the patience of the <hi>Mad Duke,</hi> that undertook without. <hi>Staff, Whip,</hi> or <hi>Goad,</hi> to drive two <hi>Snails</hi> from <hi>Milan</hi> to <hi>Moſco.. Roven</hi>is ſcituate in a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Valley on the River <hi>Sein;</hi> the Houſes are high, in ſome places Wood, in others Stone, and ſome of both, without uniformity or or Beauty. What remains of the Bridge is a fine piece of Work, and the River is about the breadth of the <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>Fulham.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Town-Wall, and the River is their <hi>Exchange,</hi> a place paved with ſmooth Pebble-ſtones about a hundred yards long, in breadth twenty, and is a fine walk in <hi>Fair-Weather,</hi> and in <hi>Wet,</hi> you muſt ſeek another.</p>
            <p>In this Town are Thirty two Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, beſides Abbies, and Religious houſes, of which the moſt beautiful is that of <hi>St. And Ooven,</hi> the Seat and Church of the Arch Biſhop is <hi>Noſtre Dame,</hi> more gorgeous on the out ſide, than Beautiful or <hi>Rich</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Behind the High Altar is the Remains of the <hi>Duke of Bedford's</hi> Tomb, ſometimes Regent of <hi>France,</hi> which was Defaced out of pure ſpight to his memory long ſince his Death, that made all <hi>France</hi> tremble when he was alive. Eaſt ward of this Church is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55316:9"/>our <hi>Lady's Chappel,</hi> a pretty neat piece of Work, but disfigur'd within by <hi>Lying Imagery.</hi> The Houſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> is in the form of a Quadrangle, a very ſtately and graceful Pile of Building; that at <hi>Paris</hi> is but a <hi>Chaos,</hi> or Bauble to it; and the Palace of the <hi>Loure,</hi> has nothing in it comparable to this goodly Edifice.</p>
            <p>In our Journey from <hi>Rouen</hi> we were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accommodated than when we came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; we were preferred <hi>Ab Aſinus ad Equos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney thither, and how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> from a <hi>Cart</hi> to a <hi>Waggon,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> call it a Coach, by the ſame Figure that they call'd a Cart a Chariot. Theſe Waggons are the common Conveniences for Travel, and are like a <hi>Graveſend-Tiltboat,</hi> ſeldom without a Knave or a Gilt in them. A Man might here be very merry, in a mixture of all Sexes, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Qualities and Languages, if the Fears of catching the <hi>Itch,</hi> or being <hi>Lowſy,</hi> did not diſturb it. Through a pleaſant and Plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Country of all things but <hi>Vines,</hi> and through many a miſerable <hi>Village,</hi> we came that night to St. <hi>Clare,</hi> Ten <hi>French</hi> Miles from <hi>Rouen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Poor Town God wot it is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Clare, <hi>and the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of the People.</hi>
               </note> and has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it Remarkable, but the extream <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty,</hi> and miſerable <hi>Slavery</hi> of the People, who Reap the beſt Wheat, and yet eat the blackeſt Bread, who make the beſt Syder and Perry, and yet are forc'd to drink <hi>Water;</hi> for the King's <hi>Taxes,</hi> and their Lord's extorted Rents, eat up all the Fruits of their Labours, and leave them nothing but <hi>Hunger</hi> and <hi>Nakedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55316:10"/>
            <p>On the Road I counted Threeſcore and Fourteen Perſons <hi>barefoot,</hi> before I ſaw one that had <hi>Shooes</hi> on, and they were made of Wood too, which made me often caſt a mournful look towards <hi>Old England,</hi> for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, and think how happy we were in reſpect of this miſerable People.</p>
            <p>In our further Progreſs we had leiſure to behold <hi>Mante,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mante, <hi>and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi>
               </note> and the <hi>Vines</hi> about it: They are Planted like our <hi>Hop Gardens,</hi> and grow up by the help of <hi>Poles,</hi> but not ſo high. They are kept with little coſt, and yeild pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the Husbandman, ſufficient to make him Rich, had he neither King nor cruel Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord. The <hi>Wine</hi> made here is very harſh and unpleaſant, and differs as much in ſweetneſs from the Wines of <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Orleans,</hi> as their Language does in <hi>Elegancy.</hi> The Town of <hi>Mante,</hi> might be thought ſtrong before the Invention of great Guns, having a Ditch, a Wall, and at every Gate a <hi>Draw-Bridge,</hi> and are ſtill ſtrong enough to Guard their <hi>Pullen</hi> from the <hi>Fox,</hi> and ſecure their <hi>Houſes</hi> in the night from foreign Burglaries.</p>
            <p>The laſt Town of <hi>Normandy</hi> towards <hi>Paris</hi> is <hi>Pontoiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pontoiſe, <hi>once belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> one of the ſtrongeſt Bulwarks in <hi>France,</hi> as being a Frontier. In it are two fair Abbies, <hi>Maubuiſſon</hi> and St. <hi>Martin:</hi> Six Pariſh Churches, of which <hi>Noſtre Dame</hi> is the moſt Beautiful. This Country was once in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by a better Title than that of the <hi>Sword. William</hi> the firſt, Annext it to <hi>England,</hi> and it continued an Appendix to that <hi>Crown,</hi> from the Year 1067, till 1204.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55316:10"/>
            <p>Having paſs'd through <hi>Pontoiſe</hi> and croſs'd the River, we entred into <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Iſle of</hi> France <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</hi>
               </note> ſo call'd by <hi>Meroveus,</hi> Grandchild of <hi>Pharamond,</hi> and firſt King of the <hi>Francones,</hi> who in the Wars between the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Gothes</hi> took it, and made <hi>Paris</hi> the Seat of his Empire. This Iſle, or Portion of <hi>Gaul,</hi> was the Seat of the <hi>Franks</hi> at their firſt coming thither, the reſt of <hi>Gallia</hi> is rather ſubdued by the <hi>French</hi> than Inhabited: Conqueſt having taken in thoſe Countries they never planted, for the leaſt part of old <hi>Gallia</hi> is in the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Normans, Britans, Biſcaines, Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coines, Goths,</hi> (of <hi>Languedock</hi> and <hi>Provence</hi>) <hi>Burgundians,</hi> and the Antient <hi>Gaules</hi> of <hi>Poictou,</hi> retaining in it ſuch ample poſſeſſions: So that the <hi>French</hi> only poſſeſs ſome part of Old <hi>Gallia,</hi> and are Maſters of the Reſt. But that which ſeems very Strange is, that tho' the old <hi>Gauls</hi> be in a manner worn out, their <hi>Survivors</hi> ſhould inherit their humors and conditions, being compoſed of ſo many ſeveral Countries and Originals.</p>
            <p>The preſent <hi>French</hi> are nothing but the old <hi>Gaules</hi> moulded into a <hi>New</hi> Name,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a</hi> French <hi>Man.</hi>
               </note> and are as <hi>Raſh, Hairbrain'd,</hi> and <hi>Hedſtrong</hi> now, as when <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> wrote his Commentaries. A Nation that may be won with a Feather, and loſt with a Straw. At firſt ſight a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> is as Familiar with you as your Sleep, or the neceſſity of breathing. An hours Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference <hi>Endears</hi> him to you, in the ſecond you open his <hi>breaſt,</hi> and the third you pump out all his <hi>Secrets</hi> as faithfully, as to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confeſſor; and then you may lay him aſide, for he is no longer ſerviceable; If you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55316:11"/>retain him longer, he himſelf will make a <hi>Seperation:</hi> He has ſaid over his <hi>Leſſon</hi> to you, and now muſt find out ſome body elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it to; and <hi>Fare him well,</hi> for he is a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that if you wear above two Days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, he will grow Scandalouſly <hi>Thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He has a good opinion of himſelf, and thinks he has as much <hi>Wit</hi> as he wants, and more than all the World beſides, and this and the ſhallowneſs of his <hi>brains</hi> makes him ſo <hi>Exceptious,</hi> and <hi>Touchy,</hi> that upon the leaſt diſtaſt he draws his <hi>Sword:</hi> In a Minute puts it up again, and then if you beat him into better <hi>Manners,</hi> he takes it with a bundance of <hi>Patience,</hi> and cries out <hi>Voſtre Serviteur tres humble.</hi> In this one thing they too much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the <hi>Devil;</hi> Submiſſion makes them <hi>Inſolent,</hi> and Reſiſtance makes them <hi>Recreants,</hi> for they always Grin like <hi>Wolves,</hi> or Fawn like <hi>Spaniels;</hi> and the Spark is nothing but a <hi>Puff-paſt</hi> vanity, in a New <hi>Antick</hi> Faſhion.</p>
            <p>His Table at a Feaſt,
<note place="margin">His Table.</note> is loaded with large <hi>Diſhes of Porrage,</hi> but very ſcarce of <hi>Meat.</hi> I ſpeak not of the <hi>Paiſant,</hi> for they know not what it is, but of the Gentleman. Their Beef is cut into Chops, and that which paſſes there for a great Diſh of Meat, would be thought with us but a <hi>Three-penny-cut,</hi> or a <hi>Siſers</hi> Commons. A <hi>Loin of Mutton,</hi> makes three Subſtantial Roaſtings, beſides a large Pipkin full of <hi>Pottage,</hi> made of the <hi>Rump</hi> and a Single <hi>Trotter.</hi> Of <hi>Fowl</hi> they have great Plenty, <hi>viz. foul Houſes, foul Diſhes, foul Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and foul every thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55316:11"/>
            <p>The great Skill of their Cooks conſiſts in ſpoiling their <hi>Meat,</hi> and making <hi>High Sauces:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Cooks, and Cook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Famiſhing the <hi>Belly</hi> to gratify the <hi>Pallat,</hi> and the Slovenly uſage of their <hi>Butchers Meat,</hi> will at any time give an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man a Dinner. 'Tis now time to ſit down, and whiſper your own <hi>Grace</hi> to your ſelf; for private <hi>Graces</hi> are as faſhionable here, as private <hi>Maſſes,</hi> and from thence I ſuppoſe they learnt them. That done, fall on where you like beſt; they obſerve no method in their <hi>Eating,</hi> and if you expect to be <hi>Carv'd</hi> for, you will riſe <hi>faſting.</hi> When you are Riſen, if you can digeſt the Sluttiſhneſs of the <hi>Cookery,</hi> which is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable at firſt ſight, till hunger has forc'd you to it, you may be truſted in a Garriſon, for nothing afterward will be <hi>Nauſeous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> Lauguage is indeed very <hi>Smooth</hi> and <hi>Courtly,</hi> it is cleared of all <hi>harſhneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The French Language.</note> by cutting off the <hi>Conſonants,</hi> which makes it fall from the Tongue very Volubly; yet, in my opinion, 'tis rather <hi>Elegant</hi> than <hi>Copius;</hi> and therefore is much embaraſs'd for want of Words to find out <hi>Periphaſes.</hi> It is expreſs'd very much in Action: The <hi>Head, Hands, Body, Shoulders, and Grimace,</hi> all concur in a <hi>Modiſh</hi> Pronunciation, and he that would ſpeak it with a <hi>Bonne Grace,</hi> muſt have much in him of the <hi>Mimick.</hi> It is enrich'd with a great number of Significant <hi>Proverbs,</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary help to the French Humor of <hi>Scoffing,</hi> and is very full of Courtſhip, if they did not Debaſe it by proſtituting their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements</hi> in too familiar a uſe of them; for the poor Village <hi>Cobler</hi> has all his <hi>Cringes,</hi> and his <hi>Eau beniſt de Cour,</hi> his Court-Holy Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55316:12"/>tas ready, and in as great Perfection as the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all their <hi>Paſſado</hi>'s of <hi>Courtſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelves with much variety of <hi>Geſture,</hi> and 'twould be worth your <hi>Patience,</hi> were it cuſtomary among <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of other Nations; but the <hi>Affectation</hi> of it is <hi>bauld</hi> and <hi>Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous:</hi> Beſides they undervalue their <hi>Courtſhip,</hi> in beſtowing the higheſt Titles upon perſons of the meaneſt condition: The <hi>Begger</hi> begets <hi>Monſieurs</hi> and <hi>Madams</hi> to his <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as familiarly as the King of <hi>France,</hi> and he can ſcarce put up the Affront, not to be thought a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>His Diſcourſe commonly runs on two Wheels,
<note place="margin">Their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and Gallantry!</note> Treaſon or Ribaldry: In the firſt he Abuſes his <hi>Prince,</hi> and the <hi>Court,</hi> and in the other himſelf, in boaſting of the many <hi>Women</hi> he ſays he has <hi>Proſtituted.</hi> Fooliſh Braggadocia's, by whom each Debauchery is twice committed, in the Act, and in boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Filthineſs. By themſelves they meaſure others, accounting them <hi>Idects</hi> and mean Soul'd <hi>Wretches,</hi> that don't Unman themſelves in theſe <hi>Beaſtialities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This brings me to ſpeak of the <hi>French Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of</hi> French <hi>Woman.</hi>
               </note> who are generally of an Indifferent Stature, their Bodies Strait, and their Waſts ſmall, but whether of this ſhape by Nature or Art, I am not able to Determine, for their Shoulders and Backs are ſo broad, that they hold no Proportion with their <hi>Middles.</hi> Their <hi>Hands</hi> are the beſt Ornaments of their Bodies, long white and Slender, and were their <hi>Faces</hi> agreeable, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Eye might think them tolerable; but here I meet with a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55316:12"/>for the <hi>Hand</hi> that is the beſt part of the <hi>Structure,</hi> in the generality of Maids that we ſaw, and their Wriſts, were ſo over run with <hi>Scabs,</hi> that you would have thought them <hi>Leapers.</hi> Their Hair is black even to a Fault, their Faces become their Hair, as a Field <hi>Argent</hi> does a Sable Bearing, and <hi>Don Quixot</hi> did not ſo meritoriouſly aſſume the Name of the <hi>Knight of the ill favour'd Face,</hi> as theſe <hi>Damo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiles</hi> do; which confirm'd me in the opinion, that <hi>England</hi> was not only a <hi>Paradice</hi> for Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in reſpect of their <hi>Privileges,</hi> but alſo a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of Women, in Reſpect of their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot collect a better Character of a <hi>French-woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Continually Babling.</note> than from her continual <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> and <hi>Babling,</hi> which is tedious, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and infinite, and you will ſooner want <hi>Eares</hi> than ſhe a <hi>Tongue. Horace</hi>'s Eternal Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, in his <hi>Ninth Satyr,</hi> was but a <hi>Puny</hi> to her. Had <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> been acquainted with her, it would have ſaved him a great deal of Labour in ſearching after a <hi>Perpetual Motion,</hi> and it would have freed him from a <hi>Hereſy</hi> which ſtill infects his Doctrin, and that is <hi>Quicquid movetur, ab alio movetur;</hi> for their <hi>Tongues</hi> moves themſelves, and make their own oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of diſcourſing. When they are going they are like a Pendulum <hi>Watch,</hi> you need not <hi>Wind</hi> them up above <hi>Once</hi> in <hi>Eight</hi> and <hi>Forty Hours,</hi> for ſo long will the <hi>Chain</hi> of their <hi>Clacks</hi> be Unwinding. A Madam of <hi>Paris</hi> came with us in a Waggon from <hi>Rouen:</hi> Fourteen hours were we together, of which time, I'le be ſworn upon a Book, her <hi>Tongue</hi> fretted away Eleven hours and Fifty ſeven
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55316:13"/>Minutes; ſuch <hi>Everlaſting Talkers</hi> are they all, that they will want <hi>Breath</hi> ſooner than <hi>Words,</hi> and are ſcarce Silent in the <hi>Grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they are Endleſs in their <hi>Talk,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and Smutty.</note> ſo are they regardleſs of the <hi>Company</hi> they Speak in, Stranger or Acquaintance, 'tis all one to them; tho' indeed no man is a <hi>Stranger</hi> to them, for in the firſt hour they ever ſaw you, they will be as <hi>familiar</hi> and <hi>merry</hi> with you, as if they had been at your Mother's <hi>Labour.</hi> Some of them I believe are <hi>Chaſt,</hi> but you will hardly think ſo by their <hi>Behaviour.</hi> They abound with <hi>Laughter</hi> and <hi>Toying,</hi> and are never without <hi>Smutty Songs,</hi> which they chant in all Company whatſoever; inſomuch that you would think <hi>Modeſty</hi> had never been there, or was quite baniſhed the Country. <hi>Maids</hi> and <hi>Wives</hi> are both ſick of this Diſeaſe, tho' not both ſo deſperately. The Ladies of the Court, I am told, as far exceed them in <hi>Gameſomneſs,</hi> as they do in the Dignities of their <hi>Places,</hi> and, I hear, if <hi>Modeſty</hi> were the beſt Apparel for <hi>Women,</hi> many Court Ladies would be <hi>Thinly</hi> Cloath'd, or elſe go <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They <hi>Rail</hi> at the Cuſtom of Saluting <hi>Engliſh Women</hi> with a Kiſs,
<note place="margin">Their Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery at Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Womens being Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and ſay, <hi>A Woman that will be Kiſs'd, is half Whored;</hi> which makes them very ſparing of receiving ſuch <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes;</hi> but this is only a diſſembled Un will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs, for theſe <hi>Damoiſelles</hi> will hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe a Man's <hi>Bed,</hi> tho' Education has taught them to fly from his <hi>Lips;</hi> Night, and the <hi>Curtains</hi> may conceal the one, the other can obtain no <hi>Pardon</hi> in the Eye of ſuch as happen to obſerve it. Upon this ground
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55316:13"/>your <hi>French Traveller,</hi> that perhaps may ſee his Hoſteſs <hi>kiſs'd</hi> at <hi>Dover,</hi> and ſee a <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſalute a <hi>Lady</hi> in the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> relates at coming Home, ſtrange Chymera's of the <hi>Engliſh Modeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To encourage this Opinion,
<note place="margin">French <hi>Boaſting, and being Bubled.</hi>
               </note> he tells his Comrades what <hi>Merchants Wives</hi> he enjoy'd at <hi>London,</hi> and with how much <hi>familiarity</hi> he was entertain'd by a <hi>Lady at Weſtminſter,</hi> when all is groſs <hi>Slander,</hi> and the Fop was <hi>Bubled:</hi> For when the <hi>Monſieurs</hi> come over with their Pockets full of <hi>Lewis d' Or's,</hi> the <hi>French Pimps</hi> in <hi>London</hi> that wait for ſuch <hi>Booties,</hi> grow into their Acquaintance, and promiſe the <hi>Heated Fops</hi> the Embraces of ſuch a choice a <hi>Beauty</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> or of ſuch a <hi>Lady</hi> of the <hi>Court;</hi> but as <hi>Ixion</hi> expected <hi>Juno,</hi> and embraced a <hi>Cloud,</hi> ſo thoſe beguiled <hi>Wretches,</hi> inſtead of the Eminent Perſons named to them, take into their <hi>Boſoms</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>proſtituted Crack</hi> of the Town, and are cheated by their own Country <hi>Pandors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I return again to the French Women,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Liberty allowed to</hi> French <hi>Women in being Courted.</hi>
               </note> and tho' I muſt not kiſs them, which every one that ſees them will have good cauſe to <hi>bleſs</hi> his Starrs for; yet they are at Liberty to be <hi>Courted,</hi> and have a greater Freedom in this, than a moderate <hi>Wiſdom</hi> would allow them. Five Meals a day, and being <hi>Courted</hi> at <hi>Church,</hi> and even in the preſence of her <hi>Husband</hi> are her <hi>Jura Conjugalia,</hi> and they will walk <hi>Arm</hi> in <hi>Arm</hi> about the Streets, or in the Fields, with their <hi>Privado,</hi> without the leaſt Suſpicion, or Imputation; which, conſidering their <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> is a Liberty ſomewhat of the largeſt, and yet they enjoy it both <hi>Maids</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55316:14"/>Women. And ſo I take my leave of the <hi>French-men and Women</hi> ſo much extold, for all thoſe Graces that may Enoble and Adorn both <hi>Sexes,</hi> by ſome of our Engliſh Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors; for my part I can diſcern nothing in them, or about them to be Admired, or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed them, but their <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as we were over the Brigde of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Iſle of</hi> France.</note> we entred into the <hi>Iſle of France,</hi> upon the Plain of a <hi>Mountain;</hi> but ſuch a <hi>Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> one, as is not to be equall'd by any <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> out of <hi>France;</hi> for if ever Nature was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of her <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> or ſcattered them with an over plentiful hand, it was in this Iſland. For three Miles together the <hi>Vines</hi> grew up in an equal Height, and afford better Wine than <hi>Normandy,</hi> or <hi>Gaſcoin,</hi> indeed the beſt on the Continent, <hi>Orleans</hi> excepted; and yet this was but a <hi>Scrap</hi> to ſtay our Stomachs, leſt we ſhould Surfeit in the <hi>Valley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we beheld <hi>Nature</hi> in her chiefeſt Glory.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Valley of</hi> Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marancy.</note> The Fields interchangeably planted with <hi>Wheat</hi> and <hi>Vines,</hi> beautified here and there with <hi>Cherry-Trees,</hi> which gratified the Eye, with ſuch a pleaſant Object, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Mixture of <hi>Colours,</hi> that no Art could have expreſſed it ſelf more delectably. To which I may add that the River <hi>Seine</hi> here di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it ſelf into leſſer Channels, to make it look like the <hi>Garden of Eden.</hi> It is call'd the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Montmarency,</hi> which gives a Name to the Town, and the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Montmarency,</hi> the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienteſt Houſe of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> who ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Firſt</hi> Chriſtian, and the Eldeſt <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and has yielded more <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55316:14"/>Mareſchals</hi> and <hi>Admirals</hi> to this <hi>Crown,</hi> than any three others in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The moſt eminent place in this <hi>Iſle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mont Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</note> is <hi>Mont Martyr,</hi> about a Mile from <hi>Paris,</hi> where, when <hi>Gaul</hi> was Heathen, many of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful were <hi>Martyred,</hi> and from thence derived its Name. Among others, which here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Crown of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> none more famous than St. <hi>Denis</hi> (ſaid to be <hi>Dionyſius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reopagita</hi>) the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Domitian,</hi> whoſe Crime was refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to <hi>Bow</hi> before the Altar of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and not offering Sacrifice to that <hi>Idol,</hi> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Heſubinus,</hi> Governour of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of St. <hi>Denis,</hi> the <hi>Patron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Denis <hi>and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Tutelary Saint of France,</hi> the <hi>Legend</hi> relates ſtrange Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as namely, when the <hi>Executioner</hi> had ſtruck off his <hi>Head,</hi> he took it up in his Arms, and ran with it down the Hill, with as much ſpeed as his Legs could carry him. Half a Mile from the Place of his <hi>Execution</hi> he ſate down, <hi>reſted,</hi> and did ſo <hi>nine</hi> times in all, till he came to the place where the <hi>Church</hi> is now built that is Dedicated to him, and there he fell down and <hi>dyed,</hi> which is about three <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Miles from <hi>Mont Martyr,</hi> and there he was Buried, together with <hi>Ruſticus</hi> his Arch-Prieſt, and <hi>Elutherius</hi> his Deacon, who not being able to go ſo faſt as he did, were brought after by the People. <hi>O Impudentia admirabilem, &amp; vere Romanam;</hi> and yet ſo far was the ſucceeding Age poiſon'd with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of this Miracle, that in the <hi>nine</hi> ſeveral Places where he is ſaid to have <hi>reſted,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny handſome <hi>Croſſes</hi> of Stone are erected to perpetuate this <hi>Ridiculous</hi> Story.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55316:15"/>
            <p>To the Memory of this Saint,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Denis<hi>'s Church by whom Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dagobert</hi> built a <hi>Temple,</hi> after Ages added a <hi>Town</hi> to it, and ſome of the ſucceeding <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>France</hi> encompaſſed it with a <hi>Wall,</hi> but ſo diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable, that it looks like a <hi>Spaniards</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Face with a two handed <hi>Ruff</hi> about it. The Temple being finiſh'd, a Biſhop was ſent for in all haſt to Conſecrate it; but our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> came the Night before with the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Angels</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed</hi> the Church himſelf, cured a Leper that lay in it, and bid him tell the <hi>Biſhop</hi> that the Church was already <hi>Conſecrated. Auditam admiſſi Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum teneatis?</hi> You may laugh at it if you pleaſe, but I aſſure you this is the Story, ſuch Ridiculous <hi>Stuff</hi> did the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> of thoſe Times invent to <hi>pleaſe</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> the People, and ſo prone were our <hi>Anceſtors</hi> to believe as <hi>Oracles</hi> whatſoever was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe <hi>Impoſtors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Relicks in St.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis<hi>'s Church.</hi>
               </note> I ſhould ſhew you the <hi>Relicks,</hi> but you muſt have patience till the <hi>Clerk</hi> has put on his <hi>Surplice;</hi> for I perſwade my ſelf, that the <hi>Surplice</hi> without the <hi>Clerk,</hi> could Marſhal the <hi>Relicks</hi> as orderly as the <hi>Clerk</hi> without the <hi>Surplice.</hi> As ſoon as he was <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and Equipt for his Journey, he put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the <hi>Road,</hi> and march'd on ſo <hi>nimbly,</hi> there was no keeping of him Company. His <hi>Tongue</hi> run ſo faſt, that the quickeſt <hi>Eye</hi> was fain to give him over in plain Ground; the Fellow that ſhews the <hi>Tombs</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> being no more to be compared to him for the <hi>Volubility</hi> of his <hi>Chops,</hi> than a <hi>Capouchin</hi> to a <hi>Jeſuite.</hi> Yet as we learn'd of him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55316:15"/>when he was out of his <hi>Road</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities,</hi> they were thus diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>On the right hand of the <hi>Altar</hi> are ſaid to be kept <hi>One</hi> of the <hi>Nails</hi> that faſtned our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> to the <hi>Croſs.</hi> Secondly, a piece of the <hi>Croſs</hi> it ſelf. Thirdly, ſome of the <hi>Virgin Mary's Milk.</hi> Fourthly, the <hi>Arm of St. Simon</hi> ſet in a Caſe of <hi>Gold;</hi> and Fifthly, the Relicks of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> reſerv'd in a little Chappel of Gold alſo. On the left hand was ſhew'd us the <hi>Head of St. Denis,</hi> and part of his <hi>Body;</hi> or rather the Pourtraiture of it in <hi>Gold;</hi> for the <hi>Head</hi> was ſaid to be within it. A Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Old Man he appear'd to be, tho' I can't believe that the <hi>rich Crown'd Miter</hi> that he wears there now, was the ſame he wore when he was living. One <hi>Relick</hi> is there, to which I hope, they won't allow <hi>Adoration,</hi> and that was <hi>Judas</hi>'s <hi>Lathorn</hi> when he went to apprehend his <hi>Maſter.</hi> A pretty one I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fefs it is, <hi>Studded</hi> with <hi>Chryſtal,</hi> through which the <hi>Light</hi> cometh, the Subſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not <hi>Tranſparent.</hi> Had it been ſhew'd me in the <hi>firſt Century,</hi> I might perhaps have been <hi>Fool'd</hi> into a belief of it; for I am conſident it can be no <hi>older.</hi> However, I will believe it to be a <hi>Lanthorn,</hi> though I cannot believe it ever belong'd to <hi>Judas;</hi> but more of <hi>Relicks</hi> when we come to <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>Relicks</hi> of <hi>Martyrs</hi> let us proceed to thoſe of their <hi>Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Relicks of</hi> French <hi>Kings in the ſame Church.</hi>
               </note> and among thoſe there is nothing that will long detain an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-man.</hi> He that has ſeen the <hi>Tombs</hi> at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> will think the beſt of theſe to be but <hi>Trifles.</hi> The chief of theſe mean ones are thoſe of <hi>Henry</hi> II. and <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Medices,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:55316:16"/>his Wife, in a little Chappel of her own building, both in full Proportion in their <hi>Royal Habiliments.</hi> Here is alſo a neat <hi>Tomb</hi> of the ſame <hi>Henry,</hi> all of <hi>Braſs,</hi> ſupported by four <hi>Braſs Pillars,</hi> his Statue of the ſame Mettal in a Praying Poſture; but the chief beauties of the Church are in the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> as the Sword of <hi>Joan the Virgin, Charles the Great, Rowland</hi> his Couzen, and that of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> IV. when he was Crowned, with his <hi>Boots, Spurs</hi> and <hi>Scepter.</hi> Here is alſo a <hi>Croſs</hi> of pure <hi>Gold</hi> three Foot high, a <hi>Crown, Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Golden Ball,</hi> given by Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> to <hi>Carolus Magnus.</hi> A Crown of Gold ſet with Diamonds and Precious Stones, given by <hi>Charles Martell,</hi> after his Victory over the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens.</hi> A fair <hi>Chalice</hi> all of <hi>Gold,</hi> in which St. <hi>Denis</hi> is ſaid to have Conſecrated the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Wine.</hi> The other of leſſer moment I omit, and take my leave of St. <hi>Denis</hi>'s Church, and walk on to <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a great busſle among ancient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
<note place="margin">Paris <hi>its Names and Scituation.</hi>
               </note> from whence this name <hi>Paris</hi> is deriv'd, which I ſhall not waſte time about, for I find the names of great <hi>Cities</hi> are as obſcure as thoſe of their <hi>Founders,</hi> and the Conjectural Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of them are ſometimes rather <hi>plauſible</hi> than <hi>probable,</hi> and ſometimes neither. The other name of this City is moſt <hi>Ancient,</hi> and moſt proper, as taken from its <hi>Scituation,</hi> and call'd <hi>Lutetia,</hi> from <hi>Lutum,</hi> Dirt, as being ſeated in an exceeding <hi>clammy, dirty</hi> Soil, but in a very Fruitful Country, and the River <hi>Seine,</hi> by Tranſporting Merchants Goods in <hi>Boats</hi> from the <hi>Ships,</hi> which lie fifteen Miles diſtant from the City, does much enrich it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55316:16"/>
            <p>It is in Compaſs about <hi>ten Miles,</hi> or ſcarce ſo much, <hi>Circular</hi> in its figure, and is a fair and goodly City, yet nothing like the <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> that ſome would make it; for was the <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi> of <hi>London</hi> altered, and all the Houſes caſt into a <hi>Ring,</hi> as it is a much <hi>Sweeter,</hi> ſo it would be a more <hi>Magnificent</hi> and better City than that of <hi>Paris.</hi> It lies Commodiouſly in a Plain, flat and level, where are no Hills to annoy it, and therefore might be made impregnable.</p>
            <p>As for the Fort near St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Gate,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Baſtile</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Baſtile,</hi> ſaid to be built by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> when they were Lords of <hi>Paris,</hi> 'tis too little to Protect the <hi>Town,</hi> and too low to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, and ſerves only for a Priſon to the better Sort that have no more <hi>Wit</hi> than to be <hi>Taken. Paris</hi> is no ſtrong Place, and if <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> IV. lay ſo long before it with his Army, it was not becauſe he could not take it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not. He was loth as the Lord <hi>Biron</hi> adviſed him, to receive the Bird <hi>naked,</hi> which he expected ere long with all its Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and this Anſwer he gave the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby,</hi> who undertook to force an Entry into it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Streets</hi> are of a competent <hi>breadth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Streets of</hi> Paris.</note> well Pitch'd under Foot with fair large Pebbles by <hi>Philip Auguſtus, Anno</hi> 1223. before which time it was miſerable <hi>Dirty,</hi> and almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable, and as it is now, every little <hi>Rain</hi> makes it very <hi>ſtippery</hi> and <hi>dangerous,</hi> and a continuance of <hi>warm Weather</hi> makes it <hi>ſtink</hi> horribly, and becomes very Poiſonous, but whether it proceeds from the nature of the <hi>Ground,</hi> the <hi>Sluttiſhneſs</hi> of the People in their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55316:17"/>
               <hi>Houſes,</hi> or the neglect of the <hi>Scavengers,</hi> or from all of them, I will not determine. This I am confident of, that the <hi>naſtieſt</hi> Lane in <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> is Frankencenſe and Juniper to the ſweeteſt Streets in <hi>Paris.</hi> The ancient <hi>By-word</hi> was, <hi>It ſtains like the Dirt of</hi> Paris; but had I power to make a <hi>Proverb,</hi> I would change it into, <hi>It ſtinks like the Dirt of</hi> Paris, and then the <hi>By word</hi> would be ten times more <hi>Orthodox;</hi> for though I have ſaid ſomething of the ſtrength of the <hi>Town,</hi> and its Fortification, without doubt, the <hi>Venom</hi> of the <hi>Streets,</hi> and the <hi>Sluttery</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> is a greater ſecurity to the <hi>Town,</hi> than all the <hi>Ditches, Forts, Towers</hi> and <hi>Bulwarks</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to it.</p>
            <p>'Twas therefore not injudiciouſly ſaid of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman in <hi>Railery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt City in</hi> Europe.</note> that <hi>Paris</hi> was the ſtrongeſt Town in <hi>Europe,</hi> alluding to the noiſom ſmells, for it is a Place of ſuch ſtrange Qualities, that you can't live in it in <hi>Summer</hi> without danger of being <hi>Suffocated</hi> with <hi>ſtink,</hi> nor in <hi>Winter</hi> without <hi>myring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Buildings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Houſes and Signs in</hi> Paris.</note> I confeſs, are Handſom and Uniform to the Streetward, but <hi>London</hi> is much finer, and the Houſes better furniſh'd and contriv'd, Their Houſes are diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Signs,</hi> as with us, and under every Sign is written in <hi>Capitals</hi> what Sign it is, nor is it more than needs, for to tell that this is a <hi>Cock,</hi> and this a <hi>Bull,</hi> was never more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in the <hi>Infancy</hi> of Painting, than now in this City; for ſo hideouſly, and without <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance</hi> to the thing ſignified, are moſt of their Signs, that I may without danger ſay, if a <hi>Hen</hi> would not ſcratch better <hi>Pictures</hi> on a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55316:17"/>
               <hi>Dunghill,</hi> than they hang out before their Doors, I would ſend her to my <hi>Hoſteſs</hi> at <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes</hi> to be Executed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The chief Artiſts in</hi> Paris.</note> The Artificers in <hi>Paris</hi> are a ſlovenly Generation in their Trades, as well as in their Houſes; and <hi>Barbers, Fidlers, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> and <hi>Taylors,</hi> are the only fine Fellows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. Their moſt curious <hi>Artiſts</hi> are Makers of <hi>Combs, Tweezers, Tooth-Picks</hi> and <hi>Comb-Bruſhes.</hi> Their <hi>Mercers</hi> are but one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree above <hi>Pedlers,</hi> and <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet</hi> has more <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> in it than this whole <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Suburbs. Merchants</hi> they have not many, nor wealthy, and that one ſhould give <hi>twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pound</hi> with a Daughter, as in <hi>England,</hi> was never heard of in this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Town</hi> ſubſiſts by the <hi>King's Court,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How the Town ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</note> and the great Reſort of <hi>Advocates</hi> and <hi>Clients</hi> to the Chambers of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and without theſe two <hi>Crutches, Paris</hi> would get ſuch a vile <hi>Halting</hi> 'twould ſcarce be able to ſtand.</p>
            <p>If you credit their <hi>Apparel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Riches.</note> and judge of their <hi>Eſtates</hi> by their <hi>Cloths,</hi> you would think them worth <hi>Millions;</hi> but alaſs you don't know them, for when a <hi>French-man</hi> has his beſt Cloths on, he is in the <hi>middle</hi> of his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> and carries his <hi>Lands and Tenements</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paris</hi> is divided into four parts. <hi>La Ville,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paris <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of four Parts.</hi>
               </note> the City, lying on this ſide the River <hi>Seine. La Univerſite,</hi> and that which they call the <hi>Cite,</hi> ſituate between both the <hi>Streams,</hi> in a little <hi>Iſland,</hi> and the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> which they call the <hi>Faux Bourgs,</hi> ſevered a pretty diſtance from the <hi>City,</hi> and are diſtinct Bodies from it. The greateſt part of the Houſes in them are <hi>Old</hi> and without <hi>Uniformity.</hi> The <hi>Faux
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55316:18"/>Bourg</hi> of St. <hi>Jaques</hi> is indifferent, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by that of St. <hi>Germain.</hi> The <hi>Faux Bourg</hi> of St. <hi>Martin</hi> is commended for the great <hi>Peſt-Houſe</hi> in it, built by <hi>Henry</hi> IV. Quadran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly. 'Tis large and capacious, and at a diſtance, (for it is not ſafe venturing nigh, or within it.) It looks more like a <hi>King's Palace</hi> than the <hi>King's Palace</hi> it ſelf. The beſt of all the <hi>Suburbs</hi> is St. <hi>Germain</hi>'s, and has a good Abby in it that maintains 120 Monks. 'Twas built by <hi>Childerick, Anno</hi> 542. and Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Vincent,</hi> but ſince, has chang'd its Name to St. <hi>Germain,</hi> from a Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> who was buryed in it; beſides this, there is in it a Magnificent <hi>Palace,</hi> ſcarce to be fellow'd in <hi>Europe,</hi> 'tis called <hi>Luxenbourg Palace,</hi> and another call'd the Prince of <hi>Conde's Palace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Ville,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> Paris.</note> or Town of <hi>Paris,</hi> are <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen</hi> Pariſh Churches, <hi>Seven</hi> Gates, and is Govern'd by two <hi>Provoſts.</hi> The <hi>Provoſt de Paris,</hi> and <hi>le Provost des Merchands,</hi> and the place of Judicature is the <hi>Grand Caſtolet,</hi> and <hi>l' Hoſtelle de Ville.</hi> The Provoſt of <hi>Paris</hi> has to his Aſſiſtance three <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> the <hi>Criminal,</hi> the <hi>Civil,</hi> and the <hi>Particuleir,</hi> which ſupplies in the abſence of the other; beſides other Officers more than a good many. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt</hi> of the Merchands, whoſe buſineſs is to preſerve the Privileges of the Citizens, is aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the two <hi>Eſchevins,</hi> as Sheriffs, twenty four Counſellors, and a Procurator, like the Common-Council and Recorder of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Habits are half Red, and half Sky-Colour'd. This Provoſt is generally belov'd by the Citizens, as the Conſervator of their Liberties, and the others fear'd and hated, as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55316:18"/>the Judges of their <hi>Lives,</hi> and the <hi>Tyrants</hi> of their Eſtates.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Ville</hi> is alſo the Kings Arſenal,
<note place="margin">The Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> or Magazine of War, begun by <hi>Henry</hi> II. and finiſh'd by <hi>Charles</hi> IX. to which has been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable Additions ſince.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo the <hi>Place Royal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Place Royal.</note> built in form of a Quadrangle, every Square being ſeventy two Fathoms long, the Materials <hi>Brick</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Colours, which makes it very pleaſant, but leſs durable. It is <hi>Cloiſter'd</hi> round like the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> It is ſituate in the old <hi>Tilt Yard,</hi> a place famous and fatal for the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> II. who was ſlain there with the Splinter of a Launce, as he was Tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Earl of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> a <hi>Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> is ſeated on the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt Branch of the <hi>Seine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</note> is little inferiour to the <hi>Ville</hi> in bigneſs, but all its Learning is not able to free it from the <hi>Noiſomneſs</hi> of the other. It has but ſix Pariſh Churches, and eight Gates, but many <hi>Religious</hi> Houſes. It was Founded by <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> Anno 792. at the perſwaſion of <hi>Alivine</hi> an <hi>Oxford man,</hi> Scholar of Venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> who brought with him <hi>Rabanus Maurus, John Duns,</hi> Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Scotus,</hi> and <hi>Claudus,</hi> who was alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Clement,</hi> three of his Con-diſciples, who were the firſt <hi>Readers</hi> there, and to theſe four does the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> owe its Original and firſt Rudiments of Learning. Nor was this the firſt time that <hi>England</hi> was the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> for we lent them not only their firſt <hi>Doctors in Divinity</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> but from us alſo did they receive the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55316:19"/>of their Religion, when they were <hi>Heathens,</hi> as you may read in <hi>Julius Caeſar Com.</hi> 6. which is an unqueſtionable Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and it had been well for them if they had writ after the ſame Copy to this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Colleges</hi> they had none,
<note place="margin">Their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges.</note> till <hi>Joan,</hi> Queen of <hi>Navarre,</hi> Wife to <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> Built that 1034. which is ſtill call'd the <hi>College of Navarre,</hi> and is the faireſt and largeſt of all the reſt. This good Example invited <hi>French</hi> Kings and Subjects to erect more, till they had increaſed the number to fifty two Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, which it ſtill enjoyeth, tho' the odd forty are little ſerviceable to Learning, for in twelve of them only, is there any publick Reading, either in Divinity or Philoſophy. Every College has its <hi>Rector,</hi> but his Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is very ſcanty, ariſing only out of Chamber-Rents, like the <hi>Principal</hi> of a Hall in <hi>Oxford;</hi> and the Building of the Colleges are as mean as their Revenues are poor, and indeed all <hi>France</hi> labours under the want of Encouragements to Learning.</p>
            <p>The College of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> is the Glory of this Univerſity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne.</note> built by <hi>Robert de Sorbonne</hi> of the Chamber of <hi>Lewis</hi> IX. None can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into this College but Divines, nor none under the Degree of Doctors. Their number is about Seventy, their Allowance is a Pint of Wine, (which is almoſt our Quart) and a Quantity of Bread daily. Meat they have none allow'd them, unleſs they pay for it. Theſe Doctors confer Degrees, and in their ſeveral turns read ſix times a day, three in the Forenoon, and as many in the Afternoon. Three Doctors with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55316:19"/>of <hi>Paris,</hi> are the Pillars of the <hi>French</hi> Liberties, and indeed are very jealous of the leaſt Circumſtances in which the Privileges of their Nation might be endanger'd, and on all occaſions will ſhew they diſapprove what they can't remedy. This Univerſity is Governed by a <hi>Rector,</hi> a <hi>Vice-Chancellor,</hi> four <hi>Proctors,</hi> as many <hi>Intranta,</hi> and the <hi>Regent</hi> Maſters.</p>
            <p>In publick exerciſes of Learning,
<note place="margin">Precedence.</note> the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> takes place next the Princes of the <hi>Blood,</hi> before the <hi>Cardinals;</hi> but at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times gives them Precedence, but at no time will give it to <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops;</hi> of which there was ſome time a remarkable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The King having ſummon'd an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of twenty five Biſhops to conſult a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Church Affairs, they choſe the College of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> for their Senate-houſe, and the Doctor that was to Preach before them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning his Oration with <hi>Reverendiſſimi Rector &amp; vos Ampliſſimi Praeſules,</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rouen</hi> interrupted him, and commanded him to invert his Style, which he no ſooner obey'd, but the Rector preſently riſes up with <hi>Impono tibi ſilentium,</hi> which is an Injunction within the compaſs of his Power. Upon this, the Preacher being Tongue ty'd, the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy grew hot between the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and the <hi>Rector,</hi> both Parties eagerly contending for Priority, till a Cardinal, wiſer than the reſt, deſired the Queſtion might be laid aſide for that time, and that the <hi>Rector</hi> would permit the <hi>Doctor</hi> to deliver his <hi>Sermon</hi> without a <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludium.</hi> To which the <hi>Rector</hi> conſented, and the Diſpute for that time was ended.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55316:20"/>
            <p>But <hi>Salus Academiae non vertitur in iſtis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</note> It would be more for the Honour and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Univerſity, if the <hi>Rector</hi> would be leſs mindful of his Dignity, and more careful in the Diſcharge of his Office; for certainly the Eye and utmoſt Diligence of a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> was never more wanting, than in this Univerſity. <hi>Penelope</hi>'s Suitors never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved themſelves ſo Inſolently in the Houſe of <hi>Ulyſles,</hi> as the <hi>Academicks</hi> do in the Streets and Houſes of <hi>Paris.</hi> For an <hi>Angel</hi> given them to Drink, they will <hi>Arreſt</hi> whom you pleaſe; double the Sum, and they will break open his Houſe, and run him into a Jayle. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard they could be hired to commit a Murder, tho' nothing is more common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them than Killing, except it be Steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in which they have their <hi>Captains,</hi> who command them in their Night-walks, and diſpoſe of their Purchaſes.</p>
            <p>To be a <hi>Gipſie</hi> and a <hi>Student</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In what time they take De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</note> are almoſt <hi>Synonymous;</hi> an Ungovernable <hi>Rabble,</hi> whom to call Scholars, were to prophane the Title, for they omit no Out-rages which poſſibly can be committed, in a Place which conſiſts meerly of Privilege, and nothing of Statute. Two Years ſees them both <hi>Novices</hi> in the <hi>Arts,</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> of them. So that by their Degrees they enjoying an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Freedom before the Follies and Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Youth are ſubdued, they become ſo Unruly and Inſolent as I have told you. Theſe Degrees are conferred by the <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> who ſeldom asks any other Queſtions than his <hi>Fees.</hi> Thoſe being paid, he preſents the Rakes to the Rector, from whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55316:20"/>their <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> which is the main part of the Creation in this ill managed Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
            <p>The Iſle of <hi>Paris</hi> ſeated between the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and the Town,
<note place="margin">The City.</note> commonly call'd <hi>la Cite,</hi> is the leſſer, but much the ſweeter and the Richer part of <hi>Paris.</hi> It contains thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Churches, it is joined to the main Land and the other parts of this <hi>Metropolis</hi> by ſix Bridges.</p>
            <p>The Principal Church is <hi>Noſtre Dame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Noſtre Dame <hi>Church.</hi>
               </note> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orn'd with a beautiful Front, and two To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers ſeventy yards higher than the reſt of the Church, which is an hundred ſeventy four long, and ſixty broad. At your firſt entrance on the right hand is the Effigies of St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> with our <hi>Saviour</hi> on his Shoulders, and the <hi>Maſon,</hi> as well as the <hi>Legend</hi> has made him, of a Gigantick Stature, tho' of the two, the <hi>Maſon</hi>'s Workmanſhip is the more admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; his being cut out of one fair Stone, and that of the <hi>Legendary</hi> being patch'd up of many Fabulous and Ridiculous Stories. It hath four Ranks of Pillars, thirty in a Rank, and forty five little <hi>Chappels</hi> or <hi>Maſs-Cloſets,</hi> built between the outermoſt Range and the Walls. This Church is now the Seat of an Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, a Preferment rather <hi>Intellectual</hi> than <hi>Real,</hi> for the Dignity is too unweildy for the Revenue, which is but 600 <hi>l.</hi> a Year.</p>
            <p>As at <hi>Deipe</hi> I ſaw the Papiſts Idolatry,
<note place="margin">The Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of the Papiſts.</note> ſo here I obſerv'd their Superſtitious uſe of <hi>Holy-Water,</hi> an Invention of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Citations of Scripture upon which this Foppery is grounded, are all taken out of the <hi>Vulgar Latin Tranſlation,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:55316:21"/>attributed to St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> whereas there was no ſuch Tranſlation in <hi>Alexander</hi>'s time, nor was St. <hi>Jerom</hi> Born till above three hundred Years after him. It is compounded of Salt and Water Conjured together by a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> for ſo the Words run, <hi>Exorcizo te creatura Salis,</hi> and afterwards, <hi>Exorcizo te aquae,</hi> &amp;e. This done, the Salt is ſprinkled Croſs wiſe into the Water, and put into a Ciſtern ſtanding at the Entrance into their Churches, and the People coming in, dip their Fingers into it, and make the Sign of the Croſs upon their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and think themſelves ſufficiently <hi>bleſs'd</hi> for that Day.</p>
            <p>On the Top of one of the <hi>Towers</hi> you have the beſt Proſpect of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The great Bell, and uſe of it.</note> and the Valley round about it. In one of theſe Towers is an ordinary Ring of Bells, in the other but two, the biggeſt of which, is ſaid to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than that at <hi>Rouen,</hi> which is eight Yards and a Span in compaſs, and two Yards and a half deep. The Bowl of the Clapper being a Yard and half about, and requires thirty Men to Ring it, which is never done but in a very great Thunder, to allay the noiſe in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Not far from the <hi>Weſt-gate</hi> of this Church,
<note place="margin">The great Hoſpital.</note> is the great Hoſpital of <hi>Paris,</hi> Founded by King <hi>Lewis, Anno</hi> 1258. and has ſince that time been very much enlarg'd by ſeveral <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactors.</hi> In this Hoſpital are numbred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Thouſand Beds, in every Bed two Perſons, beſides thoſe for the Officers of the Houſe, and in truth, is kept ſo cleanly, it is ſweeter walking here than in any Streets of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55316:21"/>
            <p>Next to theſe is <hi>la Sainte Chapelle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Holy Chappel, and its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</note> ſituate in the middle of the <hi>Palais,</hi> Founded by <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis</hi> IX. <hi>Anno</hi> 1248. The excellency in the Painting of the <hi>Glaſs-windows,</hi> and the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Workmanſhip of the <hi>Organ-Caſe</hi> is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Admiration. In it are abundance of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> as, the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Thorns,</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> which ran from our Saviour's ſide, his <hi>Swad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Clouts,</hi> a great piece of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the <hi>Chain</hi> wherewith the <hi>Jews</hi> bound him, a great piece of the Stone of his <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> ſome of the Virgin's Milk, the Head of the <hi>Launce</hi> which pierced our Saviour, his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Robe,</hi> the <hi>Sponge,</hi> a piece of his <hi>Shroud,</hi> the <hi>Napkin</hi> wherewith he was girt when he waſhed his Diſciples Feet, the <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> of St. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> St. <hi>Clement</hi> and St. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon,</hi> and part of St. <hi>John Baptiſt's.</hi> It was with ſome difficulty we procur'd the ſight of theſe, they were too Holy to be ſeen by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> but when they conſider'd our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was <hi>Catholick,</hi> we were admitted to view them; and <hi>Venerable Relicks</hi> we ſhould have eſteem'd them, if they could have fool'd us into a Belief that they were all ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years old, and yet neither the <hi>Blood</hi> nor <hi>Milk</hi> dry'd up, nor the reſt of the <hi>Trinkets</hi> never the worſe for wearing.</p>
            <p>Without this Chappel is the Burſe,
<note place="margin">The Burſe, or Exchange.</note> 
               <hi>la Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery de Merchands,</hi> a rank of Shops, in ſhew, but not in Subſtance, like thoſe in the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next and adjoining to theſe,
<note place="margin">The great Palace.</note> is the great <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lais,</hi> within the <hi>Verge</hi> of which are the ſeven Chambers of Parliament, of which <hi>le Grand Chamber</hi> is the fineſt, and in it is the Throne, or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55316:22"/>Royal Seat of the King, Cloath'd with <hi>Purple Velvet</hi> when they expect him, and at other times naked. This Court of Parliament was Inſtituted for the preſervation of the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges</hi> of the People, and was anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently of great Authority, but now is dwindl'd into nothing in that reſpect, and they now only ſit to diſpatch what the King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them.</p>
            <p>The King's Palace is ſeated on the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the <hi>Ville</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The King's Palace, or the</hi> L'Ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre.</note> hard by <hi>Port Neuf,</hi> and the new Bridge, built by <hi>Philip Auguſ
tus, Anno</hi> 1214. and intended for a Caſtle. It is call'd the <hi>Louvre</hi> quaſi <hi>l' Ouvre,</hi> or <hi>the Work,</hi> by way of excellency. The <hi>French</hi> Writers have rais'd it to a Miracle, but for my part, I never ſaw any thing more abus'd by a good Report, or that more ſcandalizes the Rumour that is made about it. I expected to have ſeen ſome Prodigy of <hi>Architecture,</hi>
which would have put me into ſuch a Paſſion, as to have cry'd out with the young Gallant in the <hi>Comedy</hi> when he ſaw his Miſtreſs; <hi>Hei mihi qualis erat? talis erat, qualem nunquam ego vidi?</hi> But I was balk'd in my Expectation, and could find nothing in it to Admire, much leſs to Envy. The Fable of the Mountain which was with Child, and brought forth a <hi>Mouſe,</hi> is queſtionleſs a Fable, and this Houſe, and the Fame it has acquir'd in the World, is the
<hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ral</hi> of it;
for if you carefully examine it in parts, it will appear ſo diſagreeable to it ſelf, and the Rules of Art, that the whole does not merit the Character that is given it. The Draw-Bridges, and the three <hi>Gates,</hi> are unſightly at your entrance. In the <hi>Quadran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55316:22"/>are ſeveral Faſhions of Buildings of three or four Ages ago, and as <hi>Inartificially</hi> and <hi>Immethodically</hi> joyn'd, as if they had been jumbled together by an <hi>Earthquake.</hi> The South and Weſt parts, the Work of <hi>Francis</hi> I. and his Son <hi>Henry,</hi> are Prince like, and when the reſt of the Houſe is caſt in the ſame Mould, it may deſerve the Character of a ſtately Pile of Building. The Inſide is worſe than the Outſide, and ſo cluſter'd with many little Rooms, that it looks more like a <hi>Tavern</hi> than a <hi>King's Palace,</hi> eſpecially when you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, tho' the Chambers are well built, they are but very indifferently furniſh'd.</p>
            <p>The firſt of the two <hi>Galleries</hi> is curiouſly adorn'd with Pictures of the Kings and Queens of <hi>France,</hi> the Tables all of a juſt length,
<note place="margin">The fine Gallery:</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably Painted, and contain a perfect Hiſtory of the State and Court of <hi>France</hi> in their ſeveral Succeſſions; for under each of their Kings Pictures are thoſe of the Lords who had Signaliz'd themſelves in Honourable Actions. And under each of the Queens the lively Pourtraitures of the Principal Ladies who had honour'd the Court with their Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Virtue. A witty Invention, and as happily expreſs'd by the Artiſts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Long Gallery</hi> is about five hundred Yards in length,
<note place="margin">The long Gallery.</note> and of breadth and heighth not unproportionable. A Room built rather for <hi>Oſtentation</hi> than <hi>Uſe,</hi> and has more in it of the Majeſty than the Grace of its Founder.</p>
            <p>The principal Beauty, (if I might judge) of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> is <hi>la Salle des Antiques,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Hall of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> the Hall of <hi>Antiquities,</hi> a low, plain Room pav'd with Brick. without any Hangings, and yet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55316:23"/>in my mind, the beſt furniſh'd of all I ſaw in <hi>France.</hi> It has five of the moſt Ancient and Venerable Pieces of all the Kingdom; but herein I ſhall be thought a mean and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſhionable Soul by the <hi>Monſieurs,</hi> who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of Antiquity, both in the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in the Study of it, and are all for new things, eſpecially Cloths, as oft as they can get them. The five Pieces above nam'd, are the Statue of <hi>Diana,</hi> which was Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in the Renown'd Temple of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of a large and manly proportion, all naked but her Feet, and what Modeſty commands to be cover'd. Another was the Statue of one of the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Gods, as black as his People. Next to that grim Deity, was the Effigies of <hi>Mercury,</hi> with a Pipe in his Mouth, and all naked but his Feet. The fourth was the Pourtraiture of <hi>Venus</hi> quite naked, in her hand her little Son <hi>Cupid</hi> ſitting on a <hi>Dolphin:</hi> And laſt of all, <hi>Apollo</hi> in the ſame naked Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, except that contrary to the Mode of <hi>France</hi> he had Shooes on, but whether they were made of <hi>Leather</hi> or <hi>Wood,</hi> I am not able to determine. All theſe are ſaid to be given to the King of <hi>France</hi> by his Holyneſs of <hi>Rome.</hi> A pleaſant exchange for the Pope to give him the Gods of the Heathens, who had given himſelf to the Idols of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and I believe upon the ſame Terms the now King of <hi>England</hi> might have all the Relicks and Ruins of Antiquity in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not far from this Room,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Houſe of</hi> Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne <hi>and the</hi> Tuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries.</note> on the other ſide of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> is the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon.</hi> On the <hi>Tuilleries.</hi> I have nothing to ſay, but that they were built by <hi>Catharine</hi> of <hi>Medices, Anno</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:55316:23"/>1564. and took name from the <hi>Lime-Kilns</hi> and <hi>Tile-pits</hi> there, before the Foundation of the fine Houſe and Gardens.</p>
            <p>The preſent King of <hi>France</hi> is the Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. by the Lady <hi>Anna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The King.</note> Infanta of <hi>Spain,</hi> at whoſe Marriage, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to fall under the <hi>French</hi> Obedience, which might very well happen, ſhe being the eldeſt Siſter of the King, they inſerted a Clauſe in the ſeventh Article of Marriage, That neither the ſaid <hi>Infanta,</hi> nor the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren born by her to the King, ſhould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Inheriting any of the Eſtates of the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> and in the eighth Article, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marry'd at eleven Years of Age) ſhe is bound to make an Act of Renunciation under her own Hand Writing as ſoon as ſhe came to be twelve Years old, which was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly perform'd. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. now Reigning, was born <hi>Aug.</hi> 26. 1638. ſucceeded his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in 1643. was Crown'd by the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> June 7th 1654. and Marry'd <hi>Maria Thereſia,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Philip</hi> IV. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by whom he had only a Son, <hi>Lewis,</hi> Sirnam'd <hi>the Hardy,</hi> the preſent <hi>Dauphin,</hi> born <hi>November</hi> 1. 1661. He Marry'd <hi>Maria Anna Chriſtina,</hi> Daughter to the late Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by whom he has three Sons, <hi>Lewis,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> born <hi>Aug.</hi> 6. 1682. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> born <hi>November</hi> 19. 1683 and <hi>Gaſton,</hi> Duke of <hi>Berry,</hi> born <hi>Aug.</hi> 31. 1686. But of this great King, his Court and Government, I ſhall ſay nothing till I am out of his Dominions, and then, Sir, you may expect his Hiſtory.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:55316:24"/>
            <p>Having wearied our ſelves with the ſight of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Madrid.</note> we went to ſee ſome of His Majeſty's Houſes in the Country; and here we paſſed by. <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſo call'd from the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Palace at <hi>Madrid,</hi> after the Form of which it is built. The Founder was <hi>Francis</hi> I. A well contriv'd Houſe it ſeem'd to be, but our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney lay beyond it.</p>
            <p>A League further is <hi>Rual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rual.</note> a little Town be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Abby</hi> of St. <hi>Denys,</hi> in which is a pleaſant Summer-houſe, adorn'd with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of retir'd Walks, and a curious variety of Water-works; for beſides the Forms of divers Glaſſes, Pillars, and Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Figures, all form'd by the Water, there were Birds of ſundry ſorts, ſo Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially contriv'd, that they both deceiv'd the Eye by their Motion, and the Ear by their Melody. Somewhat higher, in the midſt of a pleaſant Garden, are two Fountains of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Workmanſhip. In the firſt is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> the <hi>Boar</hi> of <hi>Calidon,</hi> the <hi>Nemaean Lyon,</hi> and in the Navel of it, <hi>Hercules</hi> killing <hi>Hydra.</hi> In the other only a <hi>Crocodile</hi> full of wild and unruly Tricks, ſending from his Throat a Muſick not much differing from that of Organs, and had your Eyes been ſhut, you would have thought your ſelf in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church; for the Melody of the <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile</hi> and the <hi>Birds,</hi> exactly counterfeited the Harmony of a well order'd <hi>Quire.</hi> And now we are come into the Grove, a place ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contriv'd, that it would even entice a Man to Melancholy, becauſe in them Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would be delightful. The Trees ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably folded, that they were at once a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55316:24"/>ſhelter againſt Wind and Sun, yet not ſo ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenly cloſed, but that they afforded the Eye a Proſpect over the Vines and the Verdures of the Earth that were impriſon'd within them. It ſeem'd a Grove, an Orchard, and a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, ſo variouſly interwoven, as if the Artiſt had deſign'd to make one fall in love with Confuſion. In the middle of the Wilderneſs is the Houſe, environ'd with a Moat of Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-water; the Houſe pretty, and therefore little, built rather for a Banquet than a Feaſt. It was built and thus enrich'd by M. <hi>de Ponte,</hi> the King's <hi>Taylor,</hi> and was without queſtion, the fineſt Garment he ever cut out in his life. Dying, he gave it to Mr. <hi>Landerbon,</hi> and the Queen Mother taking a liking to it, bought it, giving in exchange, an Office in the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury</hi> worth 400000 Crowns to be ſold.</p>
            <p>Two Leagues from <hi>Rual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main en Lay.</note> is the King's Houſe of St. <hi>Germain en Lay,</hi> where the late King <hi>James</hi> now Reſideth, ſeated on the top of an Hill like <hi>Windſor,</hi> with the Town of St. <hi>Germain</hi> lying about it, and the River <hi>Seine,</hi> like the <hi>Thames,</hi> running below it. This Royal Seat is divided into two parts, the Old and the New, and the whole compoſes a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtical Palace. The <hi>Louvre</hi> ſo much fam'd, is not to be nam'd the ſame Day with this, in reſpect of the Spaciouſneſs of the Rooms, and the Curioſity of the <hi>Paintings,</hi> and other <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a ſtately large Walk vaulted over head,
<note place="margin">The Water-Works.</note> are the <hi>Water-works,</hi> and the firſt thing you encounter, is the Effigies of a Dragon, juſt againſt the entrance, which vomits upon all that come nigh him. At the end towards the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55316:25"/>right hand is the Statue of a <hi>Nymph</hi> ſitting before a pair of Organs. Upon looſing one of the Pipes, the Nymph began to ſinger the Keys, and made excellent Muſick. Unto the Diviſion run by her Fingers, her Head kept time, jolting from one Shoulder to the other, like an Old <hi>Fidler</hi> at a Country <hi>Wake.</hi> At the other end toward the left hand we ſaw a Shop of <hi>Smiths,</hi> another of <hi>Joiners,</hi> and the Backſides full of <hi>Sawyers</hi> and <hi>Maſons</hi> all idle; but upon a motion of the Water they all fell to work, and ply'd it luſtily. The Birds every where by their ſinging, ſaving the <hi>Artificers</hi> the labour of whiſtling; beſides, upon the drawing a Wooden Curtain appear'd two <hi>Tritons</hi> riding on their <hi>Dolphins,</hi> with each of them a Shell in his Hand, which interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſerv'd for Trumpets. Afterwards follow'd <hi>Neptune</hi> ſitting in his Chariot, drawn with four <hi>Tortoiſes,</hi> graſping his <hi>Tricuſpis,</hi> or threefold Scepter in his hand, the Water un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them repreſenting all the while the Sea ſomewhat troubled. Thirty ſix ſteps from the Front of the Manſion-Houſe we deſcended into this Water-houſe, and by ſixty more we deſcended into a ſecond of the ſame faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not ſo long as the other. At the right hand of this, is the whole Story of <hi>Perſeus</hi> and <hi>Andromeda,</hi> and the whole acted very lively, the Whale being kill'd, and the Lady loos'd from the Rock; but withal was ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manag'd, and with ſuch mutual change of Fortune between the Combatants, that one that had not known the Fable, would have been ſore afraid, that the Knight would have loſt the Victory, and the Lady either her
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55316:25"/>
               <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Honour.</hi> At the other end of the Houſe was ſhewed us</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Orpheus in ſilvis poſitus, ſilvaeque ſequentes.</hi> the reſemblance of <hi>Orpheus</hi> playing on a <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> the <hi>Trees</hi> moving, and the <hi>Wild Beaſts</hi> Dancing in two <hi>Rings</hi> about him; an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that could not but coſt King <hi>Henry</hi> great Summs of money, fince 'tis reported that the breaking of one <hi>Fiddle-String</hi> coſt <hi>King Lewis,</hi> his Son, fifteen hundred <hi>Livres.</hi> Another Door opening, we ſaw divers Repreſentations and Conceits, which would have been more <hi>Graceful,</hi> if they had not had ſo much of the <hi>Puppet-Play</hi> and <hi>Punchanello</hi> in them. By thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Steps more we deſcended into the <hi>Garden,</hi> and by as many more into a <hi>Green,</hi> where was the Statue of a <hi>Horſe</hi> in <hi>Braſs,</hi> of that <hi>Bigneſs</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> that he is ſcarce to be march'd in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide of <hi>Paris</hi> up the River,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent<hi>'s.</hi>
               </note> we ſaw another of the <hi>King</hi>'s Houſes call'd St. <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenas,</hi> beautified with a large <hi>Park</hi> well ſtock'd with <hi>Deer.</hi> In this Houſe died <hi>Philip the Fair, Lewis Hutin,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fair;</hi> but none ſo much to be lamented, as that of our Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious <hi>Henry the Fifth,</hi> cut down in the <hi>flower</hi> of his <hi>Age,</hi> and in the midſt of his <hi>Victories.</hi> A Prince truly <hi>Brave, Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Valiant,</hi> and the <hi>Alexander</hi> of his Time, whoſe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance return'd us ſorrowful into <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we reſted a while,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> French <hi>Servant.</hi>
               </note> and being deſirous to entertain a <hi>French Servant,</hi> we had ſoon our choice of many, but generally ſuch <hi>Grim</hi> and familiar <hi>Scabs,</hi> that <hi>nauſeated</hi> an Engliſh <hi>Eye;</hi> but at length ſo many making Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to us, for fear the Government ſhould
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55316:26"/>think we were Liſting a Regiment, we pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon one that lookt the Modeſteſt of all the Fry, and enquiring into his Qualifications, he told us with a brisk <hi>French</hi> Air, that he was <hi>Un Maiſtre de Fence, Un Maiſtre de Dance,</hi> and Squire of the <hi>Toilet,</hi> but ſeeing by our Countenances we were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fighters, Fops, nor Dancers, he told us in Broken <hi>Engliſh,</hi> he could do any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to an accompliſh'd <hi>French</hi> Serviteur. He could <hi>Drive de Caroch, or Squire de Lady, Dreſs de Horſe, make de Pottage, or Cook de Fricaſy, Ride de Menage Cheval, Mend de Breech, Foot de Stocking, Shave de Beard, or make Clean de Shooe after the beſt and neweſt Faſhion A le Cour;</hi> and under this Character we took him.</p>
            <p>Having now ſeen the King's Court,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Clergy of</hi> France.</note> of which you may expect a more particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in my next Packet, or when we ſhall meet in happy <hi>England,</hi> ſuffer me here then to skip over that and give you a ſhort, but true Account of their Clergy, and of their Church Revenues, which muſt needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable, ſince it maintains ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Idle, Ignorant Maſs Mumblers; for not reckoning the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> which ſhall have a Line by themſelves, which are none of the pooreſt, and daily encreaſe like <hi>Locuſts</hi> and <hi>Caterpillars,</hi> nor any of the Clergy in their New Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, there are numbred in <hi>France</hi> twelve Archbiſhopricks, an hundred and four Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, five hundred and forty Arch-Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, one thouſand four hundred and fifty Abbies, twelve thouſand three hundred and twenty Priories, ſixty ſeven Nunneries, ſeven hundred Convents of Fryars, two hundred
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55316:26"/>fifty nine Commendams of the Order of <hi>Malta,</hi> and one hundred and thirty thouſand Pariſh Prieſts, beſides Lay Officers and Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants upon all the ſeveral Orders.</p>
            <p>To maintain this large Wilderneſs of Men,
<note place="margin">Their Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</note> the Stateſmen of <hi>France,</hi> who have propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the Country, do allow to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy a fourth part of the whole; for ſuppoſing that <hi>France</hi> contains two hundred Millions of Arpins (a meaſure ſomewhat larger than our Acre) they have allotted to the Church for its Temporal Revenue forty ſeven Millions of them. A pretty Competency. To give you a taſte for the whole. The Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Aux</hi> in <hi>Gaſcoin,</hi> is valued at forty thouſand Pound <hi>Engliſh communibus Annis.</hi> The Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Alby</hi> in <hi>Languedoc,</hi> is reckon'd at fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand Pounds Annually. The Abbot of <hi>Cluniac,</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> is valued at fifty thouſand Crowns yearly, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Prieſt of <hi>Eſtiennes,</hi> St. <hi>Steven</hi>'s in <hi>Paris,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Yearly no fewer than 8000 Crowns.</p>
            <p>As for the Vulgar Clergy, they have but little Tythe, and leſs Glebe,
<note place="margin">The Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Clergy.</note> moſt part of that Revenue being appropriated to Abbies and other Religious Houſes, and they live only upon the <hi>Baiſemens,</hi> the Church Offerings of the People, at Marriages, Chriſtenings, Burials, Dirges, Indulgences, and the like, which is thought to amount to as much as the Temporal Eſtate of the Church, and would maintain them well, if it were not for the greatneſs of their number; for generalty every Pariſh has no fewer than four Prieſts, which are too many to be Rich, and there is little hopes of their Riſing, while they ſee the beſt of their Church
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55316:27"/>Preferments given away before their Faces to Boys and Children, which diſheartens them in their Studies, and expoſes them to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery and ſcandalous Courſes.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding their Wings are thus clipt,
<note place="margin">Their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</note> and that Shame and Fear does ſomewhat Reform them; yet they will often give Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a Fillip, and allow themſelves in ſome good Fellowſhip, and to ſay truth, I think them the beſt Companions in <hi>France</hi> on a Journey, but not for an Acquaintance. They live very merrily, and keep a better Table than conſiſts with their Vow, and yet far ſhort of their former Affluency when Church Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>France</hi> were only at the Pope's diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, tho' much Eaſe and very little Study, keeps them ſtill plump, and in good liking. I once Travel'd with three of theſe mortified Sinners, two <hi>Auguſtins,</hi> and one <hi>Franciſcan,</hi> the merrieſt Crickets that ever chirped. When we came to a Vein of good Wine, they would cheer up themſelves and their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, with <hi>Vivamus ut bibamus, &amp; bibamus ut vivamus,</hi> and would Toy with the Wenches like young Kitlings, with their Tails or a Feather.</p>
            <p>The Common-Prieſts of <hi>France</hi> are as Dull and Blockiſh as flitting Beetles,
<note place="margin">Their Learning.</note> and for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, can truly ſay with <hi>Secrates, Hoc tantum Scimus, quod neſcimus,</hi> we only know this that we know nothing which their Superiors know, and therefore in the laſt <hi>Roman Miſſal,</hi> every Syllable is diverſly mark'd, whether the Word muſt be pronounc'd long or ſhort. When I had loſt my ſelf in the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> and wanted <hi>French</hi> to enquire my way to my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55316:27"/>Lodging, I would apply my ſelf to ſome of this Reverend Garb; but you might as ſoon expect Sence from the next Mule, as a word of Latin from any of them; nor is this the Diſeaſe of the Vulgar Maſs Mumblers only, it has alſo infected the Right Worſhipful of the Clergy.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Orleans</hi> I had buſineſs with a <hi>Canon</hi> of St. <hi>Croix,</hi> a Dignitary that wore a Lawn Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice laced with great <hi>Decorum,</hi> and for the comelineſs and capacity of his Cap, he might have been a Metropolitan, perceiving me to ſpeak to him in a ſtrange Tongue, (for it was Latin) he very Learnedly ask'd me <hi>Num po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis loqui Gallica.</hi> I anſwering, <hi>No;</hi> he burſt out into another Interrogatory, <hi>viz. Quam diu fuiſtis in Gallice.</hi> To conclude Sir, having read over my Letter with two or three deadly Pangs, and ſix times rubbing his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, he diſmiſſed me with this comfortable Saying, <hi>Ego negotias veſtras curabo;</hi> a ſtrange Beaſt in a Biggin, and one of the greateſt Prodigies of Ignorance, that ever I met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in Mans Apparel.</p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Our Journey towards</hi> Orleans.</note> being almoſt choak'd with the noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs of <hi>Paris,</hi> we took our Journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Orleans.</hi> The Day was fair, and not ſo much as diſpos'd to a Cloud, ſave that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Noon they began to ſpread like a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to defend us from the Injury of the Sun, and the Wind rather ſufficient to fan the Air than diſturb it. You would have thought it, Sir, a Day meerly fram'd for that great Princeſs <hi>Nature</hi> to take her pleaſure in, and that the Birds which cheerfully gave us their Voices from the neighbouring Buſhes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55316:28"/>had been the Muſick of her Court; in a word, it was a Day ſolely conſecrated to a pleaſant Journy, and he that did not put it to that uſe mis-ſpent it.</p>
            <p>Having cram'd our ſelves into our Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, we took a ſhort farewel of <hi>Paris,</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that we liv'd to ſee the beauty of the Fields again, and to enjoy the happineſs of a free and clear Heaven. The Country is like the Iſle of <hi>France</hi> towards <hi>Normandy,</hi> only the Corn-fields were more large and even. On our left hand we had a ſide Glance of the Royal Houſe at <hi>Boys,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Bifectre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Four Leagues from <hi>Paris</hi> is the Town of <hi>Mont l' Herrie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mont l' Herrie.</note> wherein was nothing obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable but the Carcaſs of a Caſtle, and a Plain about it, where was fought that memorable Battle between <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. and <hi>Charles the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> where each Army run away, leaving the Field empty of Forces, and yet neither of the Princes Victorious. Some ſcour'd away out of fear to Die, and ſome out of hope to Live, that it was hard to ſay, which of the Soldiers made moſt uſe of their Heels in the Combat.</p>
            <p>Two Leagues from <hi>Mont l' Herrie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chaſtres.</note> is the Town of <hi>Chaſtres,</hi> ſeated in the faireſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of <hi>France,</hi> where it confines to <hi>La Beauſs,</hi> a Town of an ordinary ſize, ſomewhat bigger than for a Market, and too little for a City. It has a Wall and a Ditch, but neither further ſerviceable than to reſiſt the Enemy at one Gate, while the People run away at the other.</p>
            <p>Over a little River which might be eaſily miſtaken for a Ditch,
<note place="margin">Eſtampes.</note> lies the Country <hi>La
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55316:28"/>Beauſs,</hi> through which we Travel'd till the ſame Night we came to <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> a Town ſituate in a plentiful Soil, and water'd with a River of the ſame Name, which affords the beſt <hi>Crevices.</hi> It ſeems to have been a Town of ſome conſideration formerly, as we might read in its Ruins. Without the Town is a fine green Meadow, where they uſe their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations. At my being there, Sir, the Sport was Dancing, an Exerciſe the <hi>French</hi> much delight in, and it ſeems this Natural Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo rooted in them, that neither Age not the abſence of a Fortune can prevail againſt it. On this Dancing Green were aſſembled not only Youth and Gentry, but Old Age and Beggary. Old Wives that could ſcarce ſet Foot to the Ground without a Crutch in the Street, here taught their Feet to amble, and you would have thought by the cleanly Conveyance and Carriage of their Bodies, they had been troubled with the <hi>Sciatica,</hi> and yet were ſo eager in the Sport as if their Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing days would never be over. Some were ſo Ragged, that a ſwift <hi>Galiard</hi> would almoſt have ſhak'd them into Nakedneſs. To have attempted ſtaying them at home, or perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to work when they heard the noiſe of a Fiddle, had been a Task too unweildy for <hi>Hercules.</hi> In this mixture of Age and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, we obſerv'd them in their Paſtimes, the Rags being ſo interwoven with Silks, and wrinkl'd Brows ſo intermingled with their freſh Beauties, that you would have thought it a Mummery of Fortunes; as for thoſe of both Sexes which were altogether paſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55316:29"/>they were brought thither in Chairs, and trod the Dancing Meaſures with their Eyes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Inn</hi> we lay in was juſt like thoſe of <hi>Normandy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Another way of Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in an Inn.</note> and all the difference we found was in the Morning; for there we were not troubled with ſuch importunate Begging as in that Country. Theſe had learn'd a more Neat and Compendious way of getting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and Petition'd, not our Ears, but our Noſes, by the Rhetorick of a Noſe-gay, and by preſenting us with a Tuft of dead Flowers, ſeem'd rather to Buy than Beg our Bounties. A ſweeter and more generous kind of Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving than uſed in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and ſuch as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd a lucky Contradiction; for what is it elſe, that a Maid ſhould offer her ſelf to be Deflowr'd without prejudice to her Modeſty, and raiſe a Fortune for her future Husband by the Uſury of a Kindneſs?</p>
            <p>Refreſh'd with theſe Favours,
<note place="margin">Anger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville.</note> we took our leaves of <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> and the Dancing Miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, jogging on through many a beautiful Field of Corn till we came to <hi>Angerville,</hi> which was ſix Leagues diſtant. Here was nothing memorable, but that the Town had been taken by <hi>Mountacute,</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> as he went this way to the Siege of <hi>Orleans,</hi> The ſame Fate befel <hi>Touray,</hi> a Place not much beyond it in ſtrength or bigneſs, only it had more confidence (as Mr. <hi>Savage,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman once ſaid) in the Walls of Bones that were within it, than in the Walls of Stones which were without it.</p>
            <p>This Town ſtands in the midway betwixt <hi>Eſtampes</hi> and <hi>Orleans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment at Dinner.</note> and therefore a fit Stage to Act a Dinner on; and to it we went.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55316:29"/>By that time we had clear'd our Selves of a great platter of Pottage, there entred upon us three odd kind of Fellows with their Hats on their Heads like cover'd Diſhes. As ſoon as I ſaw them, I caſt one Eye upon my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-Coat, and the other upon my Whinyard, not knowing what uſe I might have of my Steel to ſecure my Drapery; but when I had Survey'd their Apparel, I quickly altered that Opinion, and look'd upon them as the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the next Gaol. Deceiv'd alike in both my Jealouſies, on a nearer view I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd their divertiſing parcel of Man's Fleſh, in good truth, were neither better nor worſe than errant <hi>French</hi> Fidlers, which in <hi>England</hi> we ſhould have thought unworthy of a Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Poſt. Without asking Leave, or paying any Reverence to the Company, they fell a ſcrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in as harſh a Tone as the Courting of Cats at Mid-night, and as if that had not been Puniſhment enough, they abuſed our Ears with one of their Songs. By that little <hi>French</hi> I had, and the Simpering of a <hi>Fille de Joy</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> that Travelled in our Company, I perceiv'd it was Baudy, and to ſay the truth, Ranker than could be endur'd by any thing but a <hi>French-man;</hi> but what could I do? I had not <hi>French</hi> enough to call them Rogues handſomly, and the Scoundrels were below a Beating. A Gang of Raſcals ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely inferior to the Dignity of a Statute, that to Hang them, had been but to caſt away a Rope, and diſparage the Reputation of the Gallows.</p>
            <p>After their ſmutty Song was ended, one of the Hanging-look'd Company, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55316:30"/>appear'd to be Maſter of the Miſ-rule, pull'd a Diſh out of his Codpiſs ,and ſets it upon the Table before us, into which, according to the <hi>French</hi> Cuſtom, we muſt caſt in our Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence. Preſcription <hi>Time out of Mind,</hi> has allow'd them a <hi>Sou</hi> for each Man at the Table, more they don't expect, and will take no leſs; no great Sum I confeſs, but 'twas richly worth the Muſick, which was meerly <hi>French,</hi> Laſcivious in Words, and Unskilful in the Playing.</p>
            <p>We are now,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The City of</hi> Orleans.</note> Sir, come into the Country of <hi>Orleans,</hi> which, though within the Limits of <hi>La Beauſs,</hi> will be thought to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of it ſelf. 'Tis a pleaſant and plentiful Country of Corn and Vines, and may be call'd the Epitome of <hi>France.</hi> The Town is ſituate on the Declivity of a Hill, with a Bridge, a Wall, and Turrets capable of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Reſiſtance to an Enemy. It is very Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, the delicacy of the Air, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſneſs of the River, inviting the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Gentry to Cohabit in it, and they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, and are a more Humane and Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort of People than the <hi>Pariſians,</hi> or any other in <hi>France</hi> that I have yet converſed with. The Buildings are like themſelves, the Streets large and well kept, and give no Offence to the niceſt Noſtril. It has 26 Churches beſides the Cathedral of St. <hi>Croſs,</hi> and divers other Religious Houſes. The Wine of <hi>Orleans</hi> is the greateſt Riches of it ſelf, and the Country about it. And in my Opinion, are the beſt in the Kingdom, in reſpect of the Delicacy of the Taſt. I have heard of a <hi>Dutch</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that taſting a Wine in <hi>Italy,</hi> called <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55316:30"/>Chriſti, Chriſt's Tears,</hi> broke out into this pathetical Ejaculation, <hi>Dii Beni, quare non Chriſtus Lachrymatus eſſet in noſtris Regionibus?</hi> Why did not our Saviour weep in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? This <hi>Dutch-man</hi> and I were for a while of the ſame mind, and I thought I had a fair Quarrel with Nature for giving us none of this Liquor in <hi>England;</hi> but we were ſoon reconciled, when I perceiv'd it was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to the Brain if not well allay'd with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for which Reaſon it is ſaid that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King hath baniſh'd it from his Cellar, no doubt to the great Grief of his Drinking Courtiers, who may therefore ſay with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial,</hi>

               <q>
                  <l>Quid tantum fecere boni tibi peſſima Vina?</l>
                  <l>Aut quid fecerunt optima Vina mali?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is a great Trading Town,
<note place="margin">Offices ſold.</note> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for Offices, which are here, as well as in the reſt of <hi>France,</hi> ſaleable for great Sums of Money, which they ſqueeze again out of the Purſes and very Blood of the Peaſants, ſaying with our Serjeants of the <hi>Counter,</hi> that being forc'd to buy the Devil, they are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſell him at as hard a Bargain as they can. Twenty Years purchaſe, is ſaid to be no extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Rate, and I have read that only by the Sale of Offices, one of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> that ſhall be nameleſs, raiſed in twenty Years, one Hundred and thirty nine Millions of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres, which is about ſeven Millions Yearly. Of all ways to get Money the moſt ungene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and miſchievous, for the Sale of Offices neceſſarily draws after it the Sale of Juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:55316:31"/>
            <p>As this Town is ſweetly ſeared in reſpect of the Air,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Palle-Malle <hi>and Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there.</hi>
               </note> ſo it has the conveniency of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fine Walks, the beſt of which is of the Eaſt ſide of the City, called the <hi>Palle-malle,</hi> from a very Gentleman-like Exerciſe much uſed in this Kingdom. In this Walk, which is of a very great length and beauty, in a clear Evening you ſhall have all the Town appear, the aged People borrowing Legs to carry them, and the younger Arms to guide them. If any young Madamoiſelle or Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs walk thither alone, they will quickly find a Companion, tho' perhaps, ſuch with whom they have yet no familiarity. Thus do they meaſure and remeaſure the length of the <hi>Malle,</hi> not minding the ſhutting in of the Day, till darkneſs has taken away the ſenſe of Bluſhing. At all hours of the Night, if it be warm and dry, you may find them thus coup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and if at the Years end there be found more Children in the Town than Fathers, this Walk and the Night are ſhrewdly ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Acceſſaries.</p>
            <p>There is another Walk in this Town,
<note place="margin">L'Eſtappe</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>L' Eſtappe,</hi> which is principally frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Merchants, to Confer about their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and other Negociations. It reaches to the Cloiſter of St. <hi>Croſs,</hi> the Cathedral Church, of the Building of which I could never yet read or hear any thing but what is Fabulous, and not worth relating. Of the Town there is nothing more remarkable than the great Siege that was laid before it by the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> and was at laſt Relieved by <hi>Joan de Arc,</hi> Maid of <hi>Vancoleure</hi> in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> whom they called <hi>La Puelle,</hi> of whom you have an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55316:31"/>in our own Chronicles. Some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim her a Saint, and others regard her but as a Sorcereſs: For my part, I will not flatter the beſt Fortune of my Country to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of Truth, nor will I think otherwiſe of this Female Warriour but as a Noble Captain.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Orleans</hi> is alſo an Univerſity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of</hi> Orleans.</note> Founded by <hi>Philip de Belle,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> 1312. for the Profeſſion of the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and was the firſt of that kind on this ſide the Mountains. It has four Profeſſors, and the Place in which they Read their Lectures, is call'd <hi>Les Grandes Eſcoles;</hi> but rather ought to be called an old Barn converted into a School, by the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of five Ranks of Forms, and a Pew in the middle; you never ſaw any thing ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely mock its name. Their Principal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour is the <hi>Rector,</hi> which every three Months deſcendeth to another; ſo that once a Year every one of the Profeſſors hath his turn of being <hi>Rector.</hi> They Read each of 'em in their turns, an hour every Morning in the Week, except <hi>Holy-days</hi> and <hi>Thurſdays,</hi> their Hearers taking of them their Lectures with their Tables.</p>
            <p>They are very Liberal in beſtowing their Degrees,
<note place="margin">Conferring Degrees.</note> and deny no Man his Grace that is able to pay his Fees: <hi>Legem ponere</hi> is more powerful with them than <hi>Legem dicere,</hi> and the Blockhead that has but his Gold in his Hand, ſhall have a ſooner Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch than the beſt Scholar upon Tick in the Univerſity.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55316:32"/>

               <q>
                  <l>Ipſe licet venias Muſis comitatus, Homere,</l>
                  <l>Si nihil attuleris, ibis, Homere, foras.</l>
               </q> It is Money that diſputes beſt with them.</p>
            <p>The Exerciſe that is performed before the Degree is taken,
<note place="margin">Their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes and Library.</note> is very little and as trivially perform'd. When you have choſen the Law you would defend, they Conduct you into an old ruinous Chamber, which they call their Library; for my part, I thought it the Ware-Houſe of a Second-hand broken Bookſeller in <hi>Duck-Lane.</hi> Thoſe few Books which were there, were as old as Printing, and amongſt them all a Man could ſcarcely make up one Cover to reſiſt the Depredations of the Rats. They did not ſtand Endwiſe, but lay one upon another, and were joyn'd together with Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>webs inſtead of Strings. He that would e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gueſs them to have been look'd into ſince the long Reign of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> would have Condemned his own Charity, for I could not believe that the three laſt Centuries of Years had ever ſeen the inſide of them, but that the poor Paper had been troubled with the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe we call <hi>Noli me tangere.</hi> In this unlucky Room do they hold their Diſputations, and after two or three Arguments urg'd, they commend the Sufficiency of the Reſpondent, and pronounce him worthy of his Degrees. That done, they cauſe his Authentick Letters to be Sealed, and in them tell the Reader with what Diligence and Pains they have ſifted the Candidate: That it is neceſſary to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of Learning, that Induſtry ſhould be Honour'd, and that on this ground
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55316:32"/>they have thought fit: <hi>Poſt anguſtias ſolamen, poſt vigilias requietem, poſt dolores gaudia;</hi> for ſo as I remember runs the Form, to recompence the Labours of <hi>N. N.</hi> with the Degree of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> or <hi>Licentiate,</hi> with a great deal more of the like formal Foolery. <hi>Et ad hunc modum fiunt Doctores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next in this City of Letters,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</hi>
               </note> as the <hi>French</hi> Writers call <hi>Paris,</hi> is the <hi>German</hi> College, where thoſe of that Country Study, and for Decency, Order, and good Government, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all the reſt of the Univerſity. A very hearty, good natur'd and loving Nation they are to all Men; but eſpecially to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Only I could wiſh, that in their Speeches and Compliments, they would not uſe the Latin-Tongue, or elſe learn to ſpeak it truly. Of theſe Ingredients is the Univerſity of <hi>Orleans</hi> compounded, and may paſs for a Learned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademy among thoſe that never ſaw one. It could ſcarce be called an Univerſity, till the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> came among them, but rather a School of Law; but they having brought with them thoſe Branches of Learning, which before, were wanting in it, it may better deſerve that Appellation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> I ſay, have a College here,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and Schools.</hi>
               </note> and in it apply themſelves with all imaginable Diligence in the Study of good Letters, and make ſuch good Proficients in it, that they exceed all other ſorts of Orders in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as having better Teachers, and more leaſure to learn. That time which others ſpend at their High-Maſſes, and Canonical Hours, theſe Men beſtow upon their Books, being exempted from theſe Duties by their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55316:33"/>Order. They trouble not their Heads with Crotchets in Muſick, nor Chanting their Services, but imploy their Brains upon Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State, ſupporting their Friends and ruining their Enemies.</p>
            <p>To this advantage of Leiſure,
<note place="margin">Their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in Teaching.</note> they add an exact Method in their Teaching, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is ſo excellent, that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſend their Sons to their Schools to have them prove Exquiſite in the Arts they Teach. To them reſort the Children of the Rich as well as the Poor, and that in ſuch great numbers, that whereſoever they ſettle other Schools be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deſolate, or frequented only by thoſe of a more heavy and phlegmatick Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In their Schools are eight <hi>Claſſes.</hi> The loweſt is for <hi>Grammar,</hi> the ſecond for making <hi>Themes,</hi> the third for <hi>Poetry,</hi> the fourth for <hi>Oratory,</hi> the fifth for the <hi>Greek Grammar</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> the ſixth for <hi>Poetry</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick</hi> in that Language, the ſeventh for <hi>Logick,</hi> and the eighth and laſt for <hi>Philoſophy.</hi> To each of theſe Schools or Claſſes, there is a ſeveral Reader or Inſtitutor, who only intends that Art, and the perfection of it, which for that Year he Teacheth. The Year ended, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves himſelf and his Scholars with him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Claſs or School next above him, till he has brought them through the whole Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Humanity. In the laſt Form, which is that of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> he continues two Years, which being expired, his Scholars are made perfect in the Univerſality of Learning, are Manumitted from their Tutors, and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to follow their private Studies, but that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55316:33"/>which is their greateſt Art in Teaching, and fitteſt for their purpoſe, is,</p>
            <p>That they do not only teach their Scholars an exactneſs in thoſe parts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which they handle,
<note place="margin">Their obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</note> but endeavour to breed in them an obſtinacy of Mind, and a ſturdy eagerneſs of Spirit, that may render them hot and fiery Proſecutors of their own Principles, and impatient of Contradiction. This I have obſerved makes all of their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to affect Victory in all their Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of Wit and Knowledge, and manage it with ſuch a Violence, that even in their Grammatical Diſputations, little Boys will maintain their Arguments with ſuch a fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impatience, as ſurmounts their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Years. And all this pains the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> take for nothing. The poor Peaſants Son having the ſame Inſtructions with that of the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, and this procures the Society, Honour from the Great, and Love from the Poor, for the liberal Education of their Children, and gives them their choice of Wits to ſupply their Fraternities.</p>
            <p>Thus do they promote their own Intereſt in all their Undertakings, inſomuch,
<note place="margin">Deſtructive to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</note> that Men of Wiſdom and Judgment have been of Opinion, that the planting of a College of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in any place of the World, is a ſure way to Re-eſtabliſh the Religion they profeſs, and in time, to Root out any other. This was the effectual Method propoſed by that Society, and their great Patron to the late King <hi>James,</hi> to exterminate <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> and was follow'd by planting a Society of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and ſetting up many private
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55316:34"/>Schools to teach Peoples Children <hi>Gratis:</hi> and you, and I Sir, who love the preſent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, have often lamented the great Numbers of that ſort of Incendaries that yet remain in our Metropolis, ſince in the ſingle Pariſh of St. <hi>Martins in the Fields,</hi> there is more than twenty <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1554.
<note place="margin">Their firſt Entrance, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Return.</note> notwithſtanding the great oppoſition made by the <hi>Sorboniſts,</hi> and all other Orders, they firſt got footing into <hi>France</hi> in the College of <hi>Clermont;</hi> and in the Year 1594. <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> a Novitiate of that Order, having wounded King <hi>Henry</hi> IV. of <hi>France,</hi> in the Mouth, they were Baniſhed this Kingdom, and were not admitted again till 1604. and then upon Limitations more ſtrict than ever. Now in this Univerſity they have many Houſes, beſides their Colleges and Monaſtery, and in ſhort time 'tis believ'd that all <hi>France</hi> will be too little for them. Out of theſe <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſes iſſue out thoſe Fire brands and Incendiaries which put the Affairs of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> into Combuſtion, and there are forged all the Stratagems which threaten Proteſtant Countries with Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there they are at the Head of all Affairs, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, and what you in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may expect from ſuch Counſels, is no difficulty to determine.</p>
            <p>I have now done with <hi>Orleans</hi> and the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney back to</hi> Paris.</note> and am preparing for my Journey to <hi>Paris.</hi> We went back the ſame way we came, though we were not ſo Fortunate to enjoy ſo good Company as we brought hither. Inſtead of the accepable Society of one of the <hi>French</hi> Nobles, ſome Gentlemen of <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:55316:34"/>and two Friars of the Order of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> we had the perpetual vexation of four Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Paris,</hi> two <hi>Filles de Joy,</hi> and an old Woman.</p>
            <p>The Artizans were ſo ſlovenly and greaſily Apparel'd,
<note place="margin">Two Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and an Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator.</note> that a modeſt Apprehenſion would have thought them raked out of a Scullery. One of them by ſhewing his Ink-horn, would have made us believe he was a <hi>Notary,</hi> but by the thread of his Diſcourſe, we fond him to be an <hi>Apparator,</hi> ſo full of Ribbaldry it was, and ſmelt ſo rankly of the <hi>French</hi> Bawdy Court; but this we need not wonder at in the Summer, for it is the vanity of every <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to appear greater than he is. The reſt like <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in <hi>London,</hi> were always babling about who were the fitteſt Men in the City to be <hi>Eſchevins,</hi> Sheriffs for the Year enſuing.</p>
            <p>Of the two Wenches one was ſo extreamly impudent,
<note place="margin">Two Gilts.</note> that an immodeſt Ear would have abhor'd her Diſcourſe, and of ſuch a ſhameleſs Deportment, that her Behaviour would have frighted Luſt out of the moſt Debauch'd Man living. Since I firſt knew Mankind and the World, I never obſerved ſo much impudence in general, as I did then in that young naſty <hi>French</hi> Whore, and I hope, I ſhall never be ſo miſerable as to ſuffer two Days more the Torment of her Converſation. In a Word, ſhe was a Gilt born to ſhame all the Fryars ſhe had Traded with. The other Female, for I dare not call them Women, was of the ſame Profeſſion, but not half ſo Rampant as her lewd Companion; for in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her, a Charitable Stranger would have thought her Honeſt.
<note place="margin">An old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> The old Woman
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55316:35"/>was ſo very old, that 'twas a Queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe had ever been young or not. It was well I had read the Scripture, otherwiſe I might have thought her one of the firſt pieces of the Creation, that by ſome miſchance had eſcap'd the Deluge. Her Face was like that of the Sybil <hi>Erythraea</hi> in ſome old Print before a Ballad, or one of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s two Harlots in a Painted Cloath over the Chimney in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Ale-houſe, or like one of the Relicks of the firſt Age after the building of <hi>Babel,</hi> for her Complexion was a more dreadful Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than that of Languages. But of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and the reſt of the Coachful, our arrival at <hi>Paris,</hi> has at laſt deliver'd us, a Mercy we can never be ſufficiently thankful for.</p>
            <p>Having thus Survey'd as much of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as opportunity would afford us,
<note place="margin">Amiens.</note> Mr. <hi>N.</hi> by whom I ſend this, having a ſtrong deſire to return into <hi>England,</hi> we reſolv'd to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him to <hi>Calais,</hi> and taking our Journey thither in a Coach of <hi>Amiens,</hi> better accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd than when we came from <hi>Orleans;</hi> for here we had Gentlemen of the beſt Quality, and in my Opinion, more Ingenious, and better Condition'd than any I had met with in all the Acquainance I had contracted in this Nation, and which appear'd wonderful, we had no vexation with us in the ſhape of a <hi>French</hi> Woman to torment our Ears with her impertinent Diſcourſe, or puniſh our Eyes with her Complexion.</p>
            <p>Thus Aſſociated,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Loup.</note> we wagg'd on toward St. <hi>Loup,</hi> where that Night we were deſtin'd to be lodg'd. As we paſs'd by Water
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55316:35"/>from <hi>Amiens</hi> to <hi>Abbeville,</hi> in our Boat were two <hi>French-Gentlewomen,</hi> one of which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving me to be <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ask'd me my Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. I anſwer'd, as I juſtly might, that I was a <hi>Catholick,</hi> and ſhe, for her better ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, offer'd me the little Croſs on the top of her Beads to kiſs, which I ſhould have choſe to have done rather than her Lips, and did as ſhe deſir'd me: Upon which the reſt of the Company pronounc'd me, <hi>Un vrai Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtien &amp; ne point un Hugonet, a true Chiſtian, and not a Hugonet.</hi> But to proceed on our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The ſame day we parted from <hi>Paris,</hi> we paſſed through <hi>Luzarch</hi> and St. <hi>Loup,</hi> and came into <hi>Picardy,</hi> where the firſt Town of Note for nothing, is <hi>Clermont,</hi> from thence to <hi>Bretaul,</hi> where we were harbour'd, and our Entertainment ſuch as in other Places, as Sluttiſh as Inconvenient.</p>
            <p>The next day about ten,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The City of</hi> Amiens,</note> we had fight of the fair and goodly City of <hi>Amiens</hi> A City very Capacious, and for that reaſon has been often honour'd with the Perſons and Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of many great Princes. Suburbs it has none, becauſe a Town of War, nor Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, becauſe a Frontier; yet the People are indifferent Rich, have a good Trade, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the benefit of the Cathedral.</p>
            <p>A ſtrong Garriſon,
<note place="margin">The Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> which in times of Peace maintains five hundred Soldiers, though the Cittadel being ſeated on a Hill in the lower part of the Town, it ſeems fitter to command than defend it, or to recover it being taken, than to ſave it from taking. Thoſe that have ſeen it, and underſtand the Art of Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſay it is Impregnable, nor am I able to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55316:36"/>contradict it; for beſides that it is a skill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my Profeſſion, we were not allow'd to go within it. A commendable Policy in this Nation, and upbraids the Folly of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who for dozen of Ale, will ſhew a Foreigner the <hi>Curtain</hi> of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and let him mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Sconces and Bulwarks, and for a Shilling more, he ſhall ſee the Proviſion and Ammunition, and walk the Round too. A <hi>French</hi> Crown fathoms the Walls of <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> and Sounds the <hi>Peer,</hi> and for a Pint of Wine one may ſee the <hi>Block houſe</hi> at <hi>Tilbury</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> which is breaking open the Fences and Incloſures of our Nation, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing our nakedneſs to Strangers. Another Circumſtance that Ennobles this Town, is, that it is a <hi>Viſedamate,</hi> and gives Honour to one of the Nobility, who is called <hi>Viſedame</hi> of <hi>Amiens.</hi> In relation to the King, it has a Military Governour, and as a Corporation the chief Governour is a Mayor and Sheriffs, beſides thoſe of the Common-Council.</p>
            <p>Another thing which adds to the luſtre of <hi>Amiens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Church</hi> Noſtre-Dame.</note> is the Church of <hi>Noſtre-dame,</hi> a Name by which moſt of the principal Churches in <hi>France</hi> are known; for they give every where more Honour to our Lady than our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to <hi>Mary</hi> than to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and for one <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Noſter</hi> that the People are enjoyn'n to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe, there are ten <hi>Ave-Marias,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence one Pilgrimage to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> you ſhall hear of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred taken to our Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> She has four times more Holy Days aſſign'd her, ſet Forms of Prayers preſcrib'd in the two Books, one called the <hi>Office,</hi> and the other the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55316:36"/>whereas her Son muſt be contented with the <hi>Oriſons</hi> in the Common-Maſs-Book. Her Shrines and Images are more glorious and magnificent than thoſe of her Son, and in her Chappels are more Vows paid than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Crucifix.</p>
            <p>Leaving our Lady, let us take a view of her Church,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Church compared with</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Abbey.</note> which is queſtionleſs one of the moſt glorious Piles of Building under Heaven. The whole Body is of moſt curious poliſh'd Stones, ſupported by Buttreſſes of excellent Compoſure, that add to the beauty as well as ſtrength of the Fabrick. The Quire is fairer than the Body, thick ſet with dainty Pillars, moſt of them reaching to the top, in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of an Arch, I am not able to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this or the Quire of the Chappel of King <hi>Henry</hi> VII. at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> is the more exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite piece of Architecture, though I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the moſt diſcerning Eye can find but little difference between them, and that difference rather ſubtile than ſound; for if ſuch Perfection may receive the word <hi>more,</hi> it may be ſaid that of <hi>Amiens</hi> is more Majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and that of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> more Lovely, and yet neither diſparage the other.</p>
            <p>The Front which preſents us with two Towers and three Gates, is incomparable,
<note place="margin">The Front and Inſide.</note> and all the Sacred Stories are ſo lively Engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that you would not think them Carv'd, but Acted, and is infinitely above the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Imitation. Nor is its Glory (like <hi>Noſtre-Dame</hi> in <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Rouen</hi>) all on the outſide, for as ſoon as you enter in, you would think the Materials were all of Gold, and that the Glory of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple next
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55316:37"/>to the Deſcription in the Holy Text is beſt read in this Church, of which it ſeems to be a well drawn Copy. <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Houſe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that the <hi>Poets</hi> have built him, was never half ſo Gorgeous, and that imaginary Palace of <hi>Ovid</hi> is verified in this Manſion.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hic Locus eſt, quem ſi verbis audacia detur,</l>
               <l>Haud timeam magni dixiſſe Palatia Regis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Partition between the Body and the Quire is ſo overlaid with Gold, that the acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt would apprehend no other Subſtance. On the top of it is the Statue of our Lady in the juſt height and proportion of a Woman, with a Child in her Arms, all either of Gold or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gilded. The Glaſs of all the Windows are moſt curiouſly Painted, and the four Rows of Pillars with Tables on the top of them, containing the Pictures of Men of the better Quality of the City and adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Country, are exquiſite pieces of Art and Admiration, and to view the beauty of the whole Structure, you would wiſh your ſelf all Eye and Contemplation; and the only trouble of an ingenious Man is, to ſee the whole abuſed to Idolatrous purpoſes.</p>
            <p>In this great Church are twenty four little Maſſing-Cloſets,
<note place="margin">Maſſing-Chappels.</note> and in that of St. <hi>Peter</hi> hung an <hi>Indulgence</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> XV. <hi>Anno</hi> 1612. that gave an Exemption from the pains and place of Purgatory, to thoſe who upon the Feaſt of <hi>All-Souls,</hi> and the <hi>Octaves</hi> of it, would pay their Devotions and Money in that Temple. At firſt, I thought this Charter a very Impolitick contrivance,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55316:37"/>for in time it would empty the Popes Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and at laſt put an end to Purgatory it ſelf; but I ſoon perceiv'd my Error, for his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had reſtrain'd it in his Bull, only to the Natives of that Dioceſs, and left all the reſt of the World in danger of thoſe fanſied Fires.</p>
            <p>Here I had the Mortification not to ſee the Head of St. <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of St.</hi> John Baptiſt's <hi>Head.</hi>
               </note> which is ſaid to be here entire, but I recover'd upon the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that in my Life-time I had ſeen it whole in more than an hundred of their Churches, beſides pieces of it in double that number, and to believe them all to be true ones, is nothing, Sir, to what I find I muſt believe before I leave this Country, and I think in the complaiſant humor I have taken up here, I ſhall not differ with them more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, than with <hi>Pimper le Pim</hi> at <hi>Epſom,</hi> nor the famous Juglers at <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my Eyes while they Pick my Pocket.</p>
            <p>In a Boat like an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lighter,
<note place="margin">Pignini, <hi>and the Story of it.</hi>
               </note> we went down the River <hi>Soame</hi> towards <hi>Abbeville,</hi> with thirty other Perſons of different Nations, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages and Conditions, but all as true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks as ever Woman groan'd for; though, many of them, by the more than ordinary Civility they ſhew'd to us, I perceiv'd were but of the laſt Edition, whom I pity, but dare not keep them Company, for fear of what may follow, which is here too ſevere and true to make a Jeſt of. The firſt thing, we ſaw obſervable, was the Town and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Pignini,</hi> a poor beggarly Place, which they make remarkable fora Victory they here obtain'd over the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but in whoſe Reign, and under whoſe Conduct they could not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55316:38"/>tell us; but add, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from other Nations confederated with them, and all put to the Sword for miſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the word <hi>Pignini,</hi> which it ſeems then was no fitter for an <hi>Engliſhman</hi>'s Mouth than <hi>Shiboleth</hi> for an <hi>Ephraimite</hi>'s, or a <hi>Fiddle</hi> for the Mouth of a <hi>Friar;</hi> but this is all Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and that which has cauſed it to be mention'd in our and their Hiſtories, was an Interview between our <hi>Edward</hi> IV. and their <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. upon a nine Years Pacification. The next Place which the Water convey'd us to, was the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Pont d' Armie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pont d' Armie.</note> now ſcarce viſible in its Ruines.</p>
            <p>Three Leagues down this River is <hi>Abbeville,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abbeville.</note> conveniently ſeated on the River <hi>Soame,</hi> which runs through it. 'Tis bigger than <hi>Amiens,</hi> but not ſo beautiful nor populous; for the Houſes are of an old Impreſſion, and there is much waſte Ground within it. A Caſtle it once had, but now that defect is ſupply'd by Mounts and Baſtions large and capacious, which, if well Man'd, need nor yield upon the firſt Summons. Without the Wall it is diverſly ſtrengthned, in ſome places with deep Ditches full of Water; the others only by a Boggiſh, Mariſh, Fenny Level, more dangerous to an Enemy, and ſerviceable to the Town than all the reſt of its Fortifications, and therefore never guarded by the Soldters of the Garriſon. They only keep Guard at <hi>Port de Boys,</hi> and <hi>Port St. Valery,</hi> the firſt looks towards <hi>Heſden,</hi> a Frontier Town of <hi>Artois,</hi> and the other towards the Haven of St. <hi>Valery,</hi> from which Places moſt danger was fear'd.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55316:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> the laſt, we took Poſt-Horſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to</hi> Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logn <hi>on Poſt-Horſes</hi>
               </note> or things very like them, for <hi>Bulloign;</hi> as lean and poor were the Steeds, as Envy in the <hi>Poet, Maries in corpora tota</hi> was their Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter; for you might not only have counted their Ribs, but the Spur-galls had made ſuch Caſements through their Skins, that you might have Survey'd their Intrails, and given a better Account of the poſition of their Guts and Piping Lungs than <hi>Le Grey,</hi> or <hi>Mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in their Maſter-Pieces. A ſtrange kind of Cattle in my Opinion they were, and ſuch as had neither Fleſh on their Bones, Skin on their Fleſh, nor ſcarce Hair on their Skins. Sure I am, they were no Kin to <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Horſes of the Sun, nor could we ſay of them, <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miferis implent hinnitibus auras.</hi> For all the Neighing we could hear from the Proudeſt of them, was only an old dry Cough, which they brought from the late Campagne in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> which in earneſt, was a great comfort to me, for by that noiſe I perceived there was ſome Life in them. Upon ſuch Skeletons of Horſes, or heaps of Bones did I or my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions never ſee our ſelves before; and yet the Monſieurs that Travel'd with us, thought themſelves well Mounted, and cock'd and look'd as great as the little Gentleman that Rides in Triumph before the Bears and Bag-Pipes in <hi>London,</hi> and almoſt ſcratched their Behinds as often.</p>
            <p>When we expected, however to find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Poſt in them, having Brib'd them on both ſides, they began to move in an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman</hi>'s pace, or like Envy in <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:55316:39"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Surgit humi pigre, paſſuque incedet inerti.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> and out of this Melancholy Gravity no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion could urge them; the dull Jades were grown inſenſible of the Spur, and to hearten them with Wands would in a ſhort time have diſtreſſed the Country for want of Wood. Now was the Cart at <hi>Diepe</hi> thought a ſpeedy Conveyance, and we envy'd the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of thoſe that were bleſſed with a Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, though it came with the hazard of the old Wife, and the two ſmutty Wenches. If good Nature or a Fright in the Journey did ever put any of them into a pace like a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, we were ſure to have them Tire in the middle of our Stage, and put us with our own Feet to meaſure out the reſt of our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Weary of this Trade, I made bold to diſmount the Poſtilion, and aſcended the Trunk-Horſe, where I ſate in ſuch a Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Poſture, that the beſt Carrier in <hi>Paris</hi> would have envy'd my Felicity. Behind me I had a good large Trunk and a Portmantle, before me a bundle of Cloaks, and a parcel of Books. So that if my Stirrups could poize me equally on both fides, I could not fall backwards nor forwards. Thus preferred, I encouraged my fellow Travellers, who caſt many an envious Eye upon my happineſs, and there was not one of them that might not juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſaid of me, <hi>Tu as un Millieur temps que le Pape,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville <hi>and its Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               </note> Thou haſt a better time on't than the Pope in all his Grandeur.</p>
            <p>On the Right Hand, and almoſt in the Midway between <hi>Abbeville</hi> and <hi>Bulloign</hi> we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55316:39"/>left the Town of <hi>Monſtreville,</hi> which we had no leiſure (than our Horſes) to viſit. It is conveniently ſeated either for command or reſiſtance, being built upon the top and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clivity of a Hill, well Fortified with Baſtions and Ramparts on the outſide, and within has a good Garriſon of Soldiers. And indeed it concerns the King of <hi>France</hi> to look well to this important Place, being a border Town, within two Miles of <hi>Artois,</hi> and the taking of it would cut off all Intercourſe between the Countries of <hi>Bulloign</hi> and <hi>Calais,</hi> with the reſt of <hi>France,</hi> and of the like conſideration are the Towns of <hi>Abbeville, Amiens</hi> and St. <hi>Quintin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are now come to the Country of <hi>Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> which, though a part of <hi>Picardy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bulloign.</note> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains to be counted ſo, and will be eſteemed as a Country of it ſelf. It comprehends <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loin, Eſcapes, Neuf-Chaſtel,</hi> and divers little Villages, and conſiſts of Hills and Valleys af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of <hi>England.</hi> Nor is it only a Country of it ſelf, but in a manner a free Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; for it is held immediately of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who without Queſtion is a very Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Land-Lady, for her Tenants enjoy a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Exemption from many Tributes and Taxations, with which the reſt of <hi>France</hi> are miſerably afflicted. Amongſt others, from that of Salt, by reaſon whereof, and the goodneſs of their Paſtures they make the beſt Butter in all the Kingdom, and a Firkin of it is a very acceptable Preſent at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Town of <hi>Bullorgn</hi> is divided into the <hi>Upper</hi> and <hi>lower,</hi> diſtant from one another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour a hundred Paces. The lower Town is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55316:40"/>bigger than the Upper, which is called the City, better built, the Streets larger, and the People richer, moſt of the Merchants inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting here for the conveniency of the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The Upper Town is environ'd with deep Ditches, a ſtrong Wall, a treble Gate, and two Draw-Bridges; a little Town it is, not above a flights ſhot over in the wideſt Place, and has but one Church in it beſides <hi>Noſtre-Dame,</hi> which is the Cathedral. The Streets not many, and thoſe narrow, except in the Market-place, where the <hi>Corps du Gard</hi> is kept. What the Out-works are, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it hath any, I cannot tell, for though it be a time of Peace, and they very fond of it, their Jealouſie would not permit me to walk upon the Wall, either within or without the Town, and I wiſh that we were not inferior to our Neighbours in the greatneſs of their Care, ſince we are equal to the beſt of them in the goodneſs of our Country.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday</hi> the 28th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>N.</hi> took Shipping for <hi>England</hi> with a fair Wind, I wiſh him a good Voyage, and theſe Papers ſafe in your Hands, with aſſurance that while I continue in <hi>France,</hi> you ſhall have a further Account of what occurs here, to</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Humble Servant,</hi>
Eugenius Philo-Patriae.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55316:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
